<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A disquisition touching the sibylls and the sibylline writings in which their number, antiquity, and by what spirit they were inspired, are succinctly discussed, the objections made by Opsopæus, Isaac Casaubon, David Blondel, and others, are examined, as also the authority of those writings asserted : which may serve as an appendix to the foregoing learned discourse touching the truth and certainty of Christian religion.</title>
            <author>Twysden, John, 1607-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 157 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64059</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3546_PART</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31870_PART</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13153608</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13153608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98140</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64059)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98140)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 753:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A disquisition touching the sibylls and the sibylline writings in which their number, antiquity, and by what spirit they were inspired, are succinctly discussed, the objections made by Opsopæus, Isaac Casaubon, David Blondel, and others, are examined, as also the authority of those writings asserted : which may serve as an appendix to the foregoing learned discourse touching the truth and certainty of Christian religion.</title>
                  <author>Twysden, John, 1607-1688.</author>
                  <author>Yelverton, Henry, Sir, 1566-1629. Short discourse of the truth &amp; reasonableness of the religion delivered by Jesus Christ.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 161-251 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Also in Yelverton, Henry, Sir. A short discourse of the truth &amp; reasonableness of the religion delivered by Jesus Christ. 1662. (Wing Y29).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sibyls.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98140:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98140:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISQUISITION Touching the SIBYLLS And the Sibylline VVritings.</p>
            <p>IN WHICH Their Number, Antiquity, and by what Spirit they were Inſpired, are ſuccinctly diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>The Objections made by <hi>Opſopaeus, Iſaac Caſaubon, David Blondel,</hi> and others, are examined; as alſo the Authority of thoſe Writings aſſerted.</p>
            <p>Which may ſerve as an Appendix to the foregoing Learned Diſcourſe touching the Truth and Certainty of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <q>Quoniam difficilis eſt inventu veritas, undique nobis eſt veſtiganda.
<bibl>
                  <hi>S. Baſil. in Prooemio Lib. de Sp. S</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:98140:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98140:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE: Together with the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Writing.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have, to my no little ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and delight, peruſed your accurate Tractate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Certainty and Reaſonableneſs of Christian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; As well againſt the Atheiſts of this Age, who believe no God at all; As the Scepticks and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderers of our time, who before they think themſelves bound to believe any thing, will firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template, and by the model of their own fallacious, and erring reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:98140:3"/>judge of, and accordingly embrace all Chriſtian Truths that are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and recommended either to their Faith or Practice. Not that I would be thought to blame the uſe of Reaſon in the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Divine Truths, ſo as it be ſtill as a Director, and Tutor, not an abſolute King, and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, in what is either above or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way paſt its reach to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend. Againſt both theſe you have directed this ſhort Treatiſe, and in it inſiſted on the only right way whereby Gainſayers may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, Atheiſts and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers converted; That is by Arrows fetch'd out of their own Quiver; Arguments drawn from the mouths of their own Writers, which they dare not, nay cannot with any ſhew of Reaſon deny. This you have
<pb facs="tcp:98140:3"/>happily done in this ſhort Book, and drawn together into one Scheme not only what hath been forced out of the mouths of the Heathens, but what the ancient Chriſtians, <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus, Tertullian, Origen, Arnobius, Lactantius,</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> as the later, <hi>Ludovicus Vives, Morney du Pleſſis,</hi> with the moſt Learned <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> have gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether upon this Subject. And though I muſt acknowledge, that I think it improper for a Lay-man to buſie himſelf too much in the abſtruſe and knotty points of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, fit only for Caſuiſts and School-men to wade through: Yet ſurely the ſtudy of the Hiſtorical and Practical parts thereof is not only commendable in, but the duty
<pb facs="tcp:98140:4"/>of every Chriſtian, ſo far to look into as his time, and abilities will permit: For certainly, every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoever is bound to be able in ſome meaſure to give an account of his Faith, and Practice: Nay I heartily wiſh more of our Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Nobility, and Gentry would employ ſome part of their time, and excellent parts upon Subjects of the like nature, by which Learning would be advanced, the Countrey they live in receive benefit, and their own Memory, for ever ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall let this paſs: Yet becauſe you have had juſt occaſion to inſiſt upon the Authority of the Sibylline Books, whoſe Writings I find queſtioned by the Learned Pens of <hi>Opſopaeus, Iſaac Caſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, David Blundel,</hi> and others,
<pb facs="tcp:98140:4"/>I have thought fit to offer to your conſideration my thoughts upon that Subject, and ſhall endeavour to vindicate them, at leaſt ſo much as concerns Chriſtians, from the unjuſt exceptions urged againſt them; leaving it then to your far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judgment to make uſe of all, or any part of what ſhall be writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as your ſelf ſhall ſee occaſion.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:98140:5"/>
            <pb n="161" facs="tcp:98140:5"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>That there were Sibylls; whence their Name; their Number, and the Time of their Living exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat there were certain <hi>Foeminae Fati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicae,</hi> Women that foretold future Events, I ſhall not go about to prove: the Records of all Hiſtory making it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. <hi>Pauſanias</hi> tells you, ſpeaking of <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos.</hi> That one <hi>Daphne</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Earth her ſelf the Preſident of the Oracles in that place.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Pauſanias in Phocicis, pag. 320. lin. 29. Edit. Francoſ. an. 1583.</note> And a little after intimates, That the gift of Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles belonged only to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men according to the ſence of thoſe that recorded events.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. pag. 321. l. 6. in Phoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis.</note> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I ſpend much pains to examine from whence they had their Name; whether, as <hi>Lactantius,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lactant. li.</hi> 1. <hi>de falſ. Relig. p.</hi> 31. <hi>Edit. Hackii</hi> 1660. <hi>Montac. excer</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 126. <hi>in analect.</hi>
                  </note> Baroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and others, from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the Aeolick Dialect, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies Counſel, as if they were Counſellers of God: Which I ſhould not ſo
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:98140:6"/>well like, whilſt it remains queſtionable by what Spirit they were inſpired; and that Phraſe, ſo far as I remember, not uſed to any other except to him whoſe name was Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Counſeller, the Mighty God. Our Induſtrious and Learned Countrey-man Mr <hi>William Howell</hi> in his <hi>Inſtitution Hiſtorical</hi> (a piece well worth the peruſal of every man) ſeems to derive them from the genitive caſe of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Howell, p.</hi> 171.</note> calling them ſuch to whom the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of <hi>Jupiter</hi> was imparted: Or whether the word <hi>Sibylla</hi> were not the proper name of the firſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hom. Iliad.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>pag.</hi> 351 <hi>Edit. Rom.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or Princeſs of them, as <hi>Euſtathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> (the learned Biſhop, and Chriſtian) in his Notes upon <hi>Homer</hi> would have it; or laſtly, as <hi>Suidas,</hi> who ſaith it is a meer Latine word, ſignifying a Propheteſs; any of which the Reader may make choice of, as it ſhall moſt agree with his own judgment.</p>
            <p>But how many in number they were, in what ages of the world they lived, and how inſpired, will admit of a larger debate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> ſpeaking of them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tac. an. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 149. <hi>Edit. Antw.</hi> 1627.</note> and their Verſes, hath theſe words, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na ſeu plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves fuere,</hi> leaving it doubtful whether there were one or more. <hi>Martianus Capella</hi> reckons only two, <hi>Erophile</hi> the Trojan daughter of <hi>Marmeſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mart. Capel. in nuptiis Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Sibylla, vel Eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threa quaeque Cumana eſt, vel Phrygia: Quas non decem, ut aſſerunt, ſed duas fuiſſe non neſcis, id eſt, Erophilam Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>janam Marmeſi filiam, &amp; Symmachiam Hippotenſis fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am; qua Erithrea progenita Cumis quoque eſt vaticinata.</hi>
               </note> which he thinks to be the ſame with <hi>Phrygia,</hi> and <hi>Cumaea;</hi> and <hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machia</hi> born at <hi>Erithre,</hi> who likewiſe gave out Oracles at <hi>Cumes;</hi> and ſaith particularly,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:98140:6"/>they were not ten, as was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, but only two, <hi>Erophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> and <hi>Symmachia. Pliny</hi> ſpeaks of the ſtatues of three ſeen at <hi>Rome</hi> near the pleading Pulpits,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Equidem &amp; Sibyllae ſtatues juxta roſtra eſſe non miror, tres fint licèt: Una quam Sextus Pacuvius Taurus aedilis plebis reſtituit; duae quas Marcus Meſſala. Plin. nat. hiſt. lib.</hi> 34. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> one of which <hi>Sextus Pacuvius Taurus</hi> reſtored, being Aedile of the common people; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two <hi>Marcus Meſſala.</hi> Theſe <hi>Solinus</hi> tells you, <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Polyhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor.</hi> were <hi>Delphica, Erithrea,</hi> and <hi>Cumana.</hi> With him agrees the Scholiaſt of <hi>Ariſtopha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> in his Comedy of Birds. There were three Sibylls,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Schol. Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoph. in avibus.</note> of which one, as her Verſes tell you, was the Siſter of <hi>Apollo,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Erithrea,</hi> the third <hi>Sardiana. Aelianus</hi> tells you of four, <hi>Erithrea, Samia,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptia,</hi> and <hi>Sardiana;</hi> to whom (ſaith he) others have added ſix, ſo that in all they are ten, amongſt which <hi>Cumaea,</hi> and <hi>Judaea</hi> are reckoned. <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> out of <hi>Varro,</hi> with whom agree <hi>Iſidore,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lact. pag.</hi> 33. <hi>Iſid. l</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>Suidas in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Antim. in Praefat. ad Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byl. Orac. p.</hi> 144. <hi>Sixt. Sen Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliot. pag.</hi> 108. <hi>Edit. Lugd.</hi>
                  </note> Suidas, Antimachus,</hi> and moſt others count ten in this order. 1. The Perſian. 2. The Lybian. 3. The Delphick. 4. The Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maean. 5. The Erithrean. 6. The Sami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. 7. <hi>Cumana.</hi> 8. The Helleſpontick. 9. The Prygian. 10. The Tiburtine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Onuphrius</hi> addes more, as you may ſee in his Book <hi>de Sibyllis,</hi> put out before the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:98140:7"/>in the <hi>Pariſ. Edit.</hi> 1599. In his account of them I obſerve this difference; he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts the <hi>Sibylla Delphica</hi> in the firſt place, and <hi>Perſica</hi> in the eighth, I think errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; for certainly ſhe was much ancienter then <hi>Cumana,</hi> if her name was <hi>Amalthea,</hi> as I ſhall ſhew anon.</p>
            <p>The age of the world in which they lived ſeverally, is uncertain, but undoubtedly the firſt of them very ancient, and ſundry of them before the Trojan War.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Onup. de Sibyll. pag.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Onuphrius</hi> tells you that <hi>Sibylla Delphica</hi> lived long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe times, and quotes <hi>Bocchus,</hi> or <hi>Boethus</hi> for it, that ſhe was born at <hi>Delphos,</hi> that <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> took ſome of his Verſes from her, which our Learned Doctor <hi>Simpſon</hi> in his <hi>Chron.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Simp. Chro. Cat. A.M.</hi> 28 29.</note> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol.</hi> takes to be thoſe, among others, by him remembred upon the year of the world 2829. But <hi>Pauſanias</hi> goes much higher, and tells you, ſpeaking of <hi>Delphos,</hi> that it was the place where Oracles were delivered from the beginning of the earth. They ſay, from the beginning of the earth there was a place of Oracles,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Pauſan. in Phocicis, p. 320. 29 Ed. Frank. 1583.</note> and that <hi>Daphne</hi> was by the earth her ſelf appointed Preſident there—That prophecying was in common between <hi>Neptune</hi> and the Earth; that the Earth gave Oracles with her own mouth: That <hi>Neptune</hi> had for his Miniſter for that office one <hi>Dircon.</hi> And not many lines after hath theſe words.</p>
            <pb n="165" facs="tcp:98140:7"/>
            <p> I have heard that ſome Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds happened upon the place where the Oracle was,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p. 320. 38. Pho.</note> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came inſpired by the vapour of the earth it ſelf, and propheſied by the power of <hi>Apollo.</hi> Which thing might very well occaſion the building of a Temple to <hi>Apollo</hi> in that place wherein Oracles had formerly been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Nay I find farther that the ſame <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanias</hi> tells you of one <hi>Herophile</hi> that uſed to give Oracles where you find this.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>— Pauſa. Phoc. p. 327. 18.</note> There is a ſtone riſing up above the reſt: Upon this the Delphians ſay that one <hi>Erophile</hi> uſed to ſtand and deliver Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; and that ſhe firſt obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the name of a Sibyll: But I find her rather in the like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner more ancient, whom the Grecians call the daughter of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Lamia,</hi> who was the daughter of <hi>Neptune,</hi> and that ſhe firſt chanted out Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of any women, and by thoſe of <hi>Libya</hi> was called a Sibyll. <hi>Herophile</hi> was not ſo ancient as ſhe was, yet was ſhe alſo before the Trojan Wars.—</p>
            <p>When I conſider and compare with theſe teſtimonies what the moſt Learned <hi>Bochartus</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Geographia Sacra,</hi> That <hi>Noah</hi> was <hi>Saturn, Cham Jupiter Hammon, Japhet
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:98140:8"/>Neptune,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Boch p. 1. <hi>Noam eſſe Saturnum tom multa do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, ut vixſit dubitandi locus. See</hi> How. Inſt. Hiſt. p. 4.</note> and <hi>Sem Pluto;</hi> in whom you may farther ſee the concinneſs of the Story, and his reaſons at large; as likewiſe that <hi>Tubal Cain</hi> was <hi>Vulcan. Boch. pag.</hi> 432. by a ſmall change in the pronuntiation, their ſounds being almoſt the ſame. It might well ſtand together, that in that time, when there was a promiſcuous uſe of all beds, that <hi>Cham</hi> might marry his brother <hi>Japhets</hi> daughter; that is, according to <hi>Pauſanias, Jupiter</hi> married the daughter of <hi>Neptune,</hi> who, as you heatd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, was a Diviner, and all this before the flood; ſo that the ſtory of one skill'd in that Art being ſhut up in the Ark with <hi>Noah,</hi> is not only probable but true; for we are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, <hi>Noahs</hi> three Sons with their wives were ſhut up there.
<note place="margin">Joſep. li. 1. cap. 5. Lil. Giral. de Poet. Hiſt. pa. 79.</note> 
               <hi>Joſephus,</hi> a Jewiſh Writer, and certainly no friend to Propheſies not owned by thoſe of his Nation, tells you of one that ſpake of the building the Tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> and the confuſion of tongues alſo, but without any mark of diſtruſt put upon it, which probably he would have done, had he found any cauſe not to believe the truth of their Writings. <hi>Lilius Giraldus</hi> tells you, That Sibylla <hi>Perſica,</hi> called <hi>Sambethe,</hi> the ſame with <hi>Chaldaica</hi> and <hi>Hebraea,</hi> lived before the flood, and was ſhut up in the Ark with <hi>Noah.</hi> I find her alſo called
<note n="*" place="margin">Lil. Giral. de Poet. Hiſt. pa. 79 Dial. 2. Suidas in verb. Collius l. 3. p. 2. p. 192. De ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabus Paganc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuin.</note> 
               <hi>Sambethe Noe,</hi> which might as well be the daughter of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> as to derive her name from <hi>Noe,</hi> a Town near the Red Sea, as <hi>Beirlin. in Verb.</hi> and our induſtrious Countryman Mr. <hi>Howel</hi> in his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit.
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:98140:8"/>Hiſtorical,</hi> incline, <hi>pag.</hi> 171. <hi>Georg. Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drenus</hi> tells you of one in <hi>Solomons</hi> time, it may be the ſame <hi>Pauſan pag.</hi> 327. calls <hi>Saba,</hi> and to have ſucceeded <hi>Demo,</hi> ſaid to be the daughter of <hi>Beroſus</hi> and <hi>Erimanthe.</hi> The Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> who was alſo by the Grecians called a Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byll,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Glycas. Annal. p. 256.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Onuphrius</hi> in his Book <hi>de Sibyllis,</hi> will tell you of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that lived in other ages of the world,
<note place="margin">Pauſan. in Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cic. p. 337. Onup. de Sibyl.</note> and aſſuredly long before that <hi>Amalthea,</hi> who is ſaid to have offered to ſale nine books of Oracles to <hi>Tarquinius Priſcus,</hi> others to <hi>Superbus;</hi> which ſtory, becauſe I ſhall make ſome uſe of it, I ſhall deliver at large, as I have literally rendred it out of <hi>Dionyſius Harliearnaſſaeus,</hi> who lived about twenty ſix years before the birth of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, as <hi>Helvicus</hi> hath it.
<note place="margin">Helv. Chron. in annot. in cat. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. illuſtrium.</note> The ſtory in <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyſius Halicarnaſſaeus</hi> is thus, Another very admirable accident in the time of the Reign of <hi>Tarquinius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Lib. 4. fol 259.</note> whether given by the good will of the Gods or Daemons, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to have fallen out in the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> which not only for a ſmall time, but in all ages, and often hath ſaved it from great evils. A certain woman, not of that Country, came to the King, deſirous to ſell nine books fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Sibylline Oracles; but the King not thinking fit to buy them at the price ſhe asked, ſhewent from his preſence and burnt three
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:98140:9"/>of them, and ſoon after returning, asked the ſame price for thoſe that remained; but he thinking her ſome dotard, and to be derided, who asked for a fewer in number that price ſhe could not obtain for them all, ſhe again went away, and burnt half of them that were left; and bringing again the three that remained, demanded ſtill the ſame quantity of gold: The King then wondring at this deliberate counſel in the woman, ſent to the Augurs,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and diſcourſing the matter with them, inquired what was fit to be done; they by certain ſigns having learnt that he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed a bleſſing ſent from God, and deeming it a great misfortune that he had not bought all the books, commanded the gold to be told out to her, and to receive the books that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained; but ſhe giving the books, with a charge to keep them carefully, vaniſhed out of their ſight. <hi>Tarquin</hi> made choice of two of the Citizens of good rank; and joyning to them two other publique Miniſters, gave unto them the cuſtody of them; one of which was called <hi>Marcus Atylius,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſeemed he had done ſomething inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly as to his truſt, and being accuſed as a Parricide by one of the publick Miniſters,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> was ſewen into a ſack of leather, and thrown in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea. But after the expulſion of the Kings, the City taking upon themſelves the overſight of the Oracles, conſtituted for their keepers the moſt conſiderable men of their City, diſcharging them from all other
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:98140:9"/>employments both military, and civil, and appointed others of the people, without whom they permitted not theſe men to take a view of the Oracles. In ſhort, let me tell you, The Romans kept no holy or ſacred poſſeſſion whatſoever, with that care they did the Sibylline Oracles: They made uſe of them according to the Vote of the Senate, when any ſedition fell out in the City, or great misfortune in war, or that wonders, or great and portentous Apparitsons were ſeen amongſt them, which things often fell out. Theſe books of Oracles remained until the time of the ſo called <hi>Marſike</hi> War, being laid under ground in the Temple of <hi>Jupiter Capitolinus,</hi> and kept in a Coffer, or Box of ſtone, by the <hi>Decemvirs.</hi> But after the 173. Olympiade, the Temple being burnt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on ſet purpoſe, as ſome think, or by chance, they were, together with other things conſecrated to the Gods, deſtroyed by the fire. Thoſe which now are; were fetch'd from ſundry places; ſome out of the Cities of <hi>Italy,</hi> ſome out of <hi>Erithre</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> Meſſengers being ſent by the Decree of the Senate to tranſcribe them; ſome were fetchd from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cities, tranſcribed by private hands, in which there are ſome things ſuppoſititious, or inſerted among the Sibylline Writings; but they are <hi>diſcovered</hi> by thoſe verſes which are called Acroſticks.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Thus far he. Others call this ſtrange womans name <hi>Amalthea</hi> of <hi>Cumes.</hi> But from this ſtory thus told, with
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:98140:10"/>which <hi>Varro Lactantius</hi> and others agree, give me leave to make theſe Obſervations.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Obſervations, and by what Spirit they ſpake is diſcuſſed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIrſt, That in the judgment of <hi>Dionyſius Halicarnaſſaeus</hi> 'twas uncertain by what Spirit they were inſpired; for he relates as doubtful whether thoſe books were given by God or the Divel. St <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaking of the ſpirit of <hi>Python,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. Com. in Epiſt. 1. ad Cor. cap. 11.</note> hath theſe words; <hi>Hic eſt qui per Sibyllam locutus eſt, &amp;c.</hi> St <hi>Auguſtine Cont. Manich.</hi> hath theſe words; Moreover, touching Sibyll or Sibylls, <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sibylla porro vel Sibyllae, &amp; Orpheus &amp; neſcio quis, Home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, &amp; ſi qui alii Vates, vel Theologi, vel Sapientes, vel Philoſophi Gentium, de Filio Dei, aut de Patre Deo vera prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dixiſſe, ſeu dixiſſo perhibentur, valet quidem aliquid ad illorum vanitatem revincendam, non tamen ad iſtorum authoritatem amp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cotendam, cum illum Deum colere oſtendimus quem nec illi tacere potuerunt, qui ſuos con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiles populos Idola &amp; Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>na colenda partim docere au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ſunt, partim prohibere auſi non ſunt.</note> and I know not who, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and whatſoever other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſagers, Divines, Wiſe men, or Philoſophers of the Gentiles, who are reported to have told or foretold true things of the Son of God, or God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, 'tis indeed of ſome uſe to overthrow the vanity of the Gentiles, not to make us em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their Authority; ſince we make it appear that we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:98140:10"/>that God of whom they could not hold their peace, who partly taught their Country-men that Idols, and Daemons were to be worſhipped, partly durſt not hinder them in it. Perhaps he may mean this rather of the other Soothſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Diviners that were common in thoſe times; not of the Sibylls, at leaſt all of them; for if our Learned Prelate <hi>Richard Mounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute,</hi> ſometimes L. Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mount. Analect p. 159.</note> quote him right, he ſpeaks more favourably of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylla Erithrea,</hi> ſaying, She had nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all her Verſes which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther belonged to the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of falſe or feigned gods.
<note place="margin">Nihil habuit in toto carmine quod ad Deorum falſorum ſeu fictorum cultum pertineat.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaac Caſaubon,</hi> a man of great learning, and various reading, ſpeaking of the uſe made of them by the Romans, hath theſe words; There was never any thing produced (he means by the Romans) out of thoſe Books,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nihil enim unquam ex illis libris prolatum quo gentium error, &amp; ille inſanus Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num cultus non confirmarctur, aut etiam nova acceſſione impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etatis non augeretur.</hi> Caſ. p. 81. ed Gen. exc. in Bar.</note> by which the errour of the Gentiles, and that mad wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Daemons was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed or augmented by ſome new acceſſion of impiety. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what he ſaith to be true; for he that is converſant in any meaſure with the Romane ſtory, will find with what ſuperſtition and impious facrifices they conſulted thoſe books, and commonly in ſuch caſes wherein the good only of their own Country, and the worſhip of their feigned Gods might be promoted;
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:98140:11"/>inſomuch that whatever elſe was in theſe books that concerned the worſhip of the true God, being by them not underſtood, was wholly neglected; and therefore, in my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Gaſaubon</hi> deſerves not the cenſure which I find he hath received in this particular, as if he had contradicted what St <hi>Auguſtine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him had delivered. <hi>Blundelius,</hi> in his Book <hi>De les Sibylles,</hi> calls them frequently <hi>Rhapſodiſts,</hi> ſtale meat, like <hi>Noſtredamus, &amp;c.</hi> And truly, it is juſtly to be doubted, whether thoſe perſons were indued with the Spirit of God, in whoſe writings, among many truths, much that countenanced impiety was mixed. We know God ſometimes forced the truth out of the mouths of falſe Prophets, <hi>Balaam, Caiaphas,</hi> and others; neither is it very mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, to examine by what ſpirit they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, whether, as <hi>Arnobius, Lactantius, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Sixt. Sen. bib p.</hi> 108. <hi>Edit. Lugd. Mont. excer.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 186. <hi>in Anal. &amp; alii.</hi>
               </note> and others, that they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, filled with Gods Spirit, or ſpake only by his permiſſion, as the Oracles did; ſo as the truth of what they foretold is for the generality made good; neither can I think it unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to believe, with Cardinal <hi>Baronius,</hi> That the Counſel of God was ſuch,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confilium Dei fuiſſe ut longe ante Chriſti adventum tantae rei ſacramentum Judais atque Gentibus innoteſceret, illis quidem per Prophetas, hiſce vero per ſuos Vates, Hiſdaſpem praecipue, &amp; Sibyllas. Mount. ia Anal. p.</hi> 127.</note> that long before the coming of Chriſt ſome ſign of ſo great a bleſſing ſhould be made known to the Jews and Gentiles; to them by the Prophets, to theſe by their <hi>Vates,</hi> chiefly <hi>Hidaſpes,</hi> and the Sibylls.</p>
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:98140:11"/>
            <p> Secondly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>2</label> That this perſon that came to <hi>Tarquinius</hi> could not be of <hi>Cumes</hi> in <hi>Italy;</hi> for ſhe is ſaid to be a ſtranger,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>, not of that Nation; and that any of any other Nation ſhould at that time inhabit in <hi>Cumes</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> and there deliver Oracles, and the Roman State not know of it, ſeems very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>3</label> It is manifeſt there were more genuine Books of that nature at that time; for we ſee ſhe burnt ſix of nine filled with the ſame matter, or two of three, as others ſay, but all agree the greateſt number was burnt, and ſo probably enough thoſe afterward ſought out in the time of the Conſulate of <hi>Scribonius</hi> and <hi>Octavius</hi> in the 176 <hi>Olymp.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Onup. de Sibyl. pag. 47. out of Feneſt. Helv. Chron. pag. 81. Ed. Oxon.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 15 years after the Capitol was burnt, which happened in the time of the War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Marſi and their Confederates, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Marſick, or Sociale War, might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain much of what was in the Books burnt by <hi>Amalthea,</hi> and which never were before in the Roman hands, and ſo periſhed not with the Capitol; and conſequently that they were not neceſſarily ſuppoſititious, or ſpurious, becauſe <hi>Dionyſius Halicarnaſſaeus</hi> ſaith ſo, who being a Heathen, judged of the truth, or falſhood of them, by their agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with what he had learned was in the former Books; by which, according to the beſt examination the State could make, what they received from <hi>Erithre,</hi> and other Towns of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> were corrected.</p>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:98140:12"/>
            <p> Fourthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>4</label> It is evident, the original Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of what the Romans received were ſtill kept in thoſe places from whence they had them; for it is expreſly ſaid, they cauſed them to be tranſcribed, which might be part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the reaſon of the multitude of Copies that were after extant of Books of that nature: Nor can I believe, that in 15 years no man ſhould have the curioſity to ſeek out ſuch ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, till <hi>Scribonius,</hi> and <hi>Octavius</hi> motioned it in the Senate, though between that time and the Reign of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> when the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Books were burnt, many more years, near 100, had elapſed.</p>
            <p>Fifthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>5</label> That it doth no way appear, that thoſe Books ſold by this ſtrange woman were the product of her own brain, but might very well be the Writings of ſome other; nay, if there be any truth in that part of her ſtory, that ſhe vaniſhed away, ſhe muſt needs be an Angel or Devil, and ſo that opinion no way impugned which ſhall affirm, that what ſhe ſold to <hi>Tarquinius</hi> was the work of ſome other much ancienter then her ſelf, perhaps hers that went by the name of <hi>Erithrea,</hi> and lived at <hi>Cumes</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> alſo, becauſe the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans firſt ſent to <hi>Erithre,</hi> undoubtedly from that reaſon, that they believ'd thoſe books they had loſt were likelieſt to be found there; and beſide,
<note place="margin">Montac. in ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. pag. 150. Oaup. de Sibyl. Lactan. p. 33.</note> I find this <hi>Amalthea</hi> counted the <hi>Sibyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Cumana,</hi> not <hi>Cumaea,</hi> as <hi>Onuphrius, Suidas, Lactantius,</hi> and others, have before taken no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, though the ſimilitude of their names
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:98140:12"/>made their perſons ſometimes confounded.</p>
            <p>Sixthly,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>6</label> That the Acroſticks in the Sibyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Books were a means by which the true Writings were diſtinguiſhed or diſcovered.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>What Writings of the Sibylls were kept in the Capitol: The read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of others promiſcuouſly not forbidden.</hi> Juſtin Martyr <hi>ſo to be underſtood.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>YOu have heard before what care the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans took to repair their loſs, by getting in again what they could of the Sibylline Books: Amongſt thoſe they obtained, <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> will tell you, they ſtrictly laid up only thoſe of <hi>Cumaea.</hi> His words are theſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Harum omnium Sibyllarum car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina &amp; feruntur &amp; habentur praeterquam Cumaeae; cujus li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri à Romanis occuluntur, nec cos ab ullo nifi à quindecem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris inſpici fas est.</hi> Lact. de falſ. Relig. lib. 1. pag. 35, 36.</note> The Verſes of all the Sibylls are abroad, and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, except thoſe of <hi>Cumaea,</hi> whoſe Books are ſecretly laid up by the Romans; nor is it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for any, except the <hi>Quinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem viri,</hi> to look into them.</p>
            <p>The curioſity of men continually increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from the time of the burning of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:98140:13"/>unto the review made by <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> which was 60 years, or upward, there were got into private hands above 2000 Copies of Books of that nature, which produced that Decree made by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> for the bringing them in to the Praetors hands; as <hi>Suetonius</hi> tells you.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quicquid fatidicorum libro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Graci Latinique generis, nullis, vel parum idoneis aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus vulgò ferebantur, ſupra duo millia contracta, undique cremavit, ac ſolos retinuit Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billinos, hos quoque delectu habito, condiditque duobus fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulis auratis ſub Palatini A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollinis baſi.</hi> Suet. in vita Aug. pag. 152. Edit. Hackii. 1651.</note> Whatſoever preſaging or fate-telling Books either in Greek, or Latine, were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly vented abroad, either under none, or Authors names of little account, having ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together of them above two thouſand, he cauſed to be burnt, retaining only the Sibyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Books; of theſe alſo he took what he liked to make choice of, and hid them in two gilded hutches under the foot of a pillar in the Temple of <hi>Apollo Palatinus.</hi> In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation 'tis obſervable, that the Sibylline Books were exempted from this Martyrdom; nay indeed none ſuffered but ſuch as had no warrantable Author to ſecure them: What he liked in the Sibylline Books he laid up in the Temple; ſo we find here a new acceſſion to thoſe Books gathered together before by the Roman Embaſſadours ſent abroad to that purpoſe: And I find farther, that after this, when <hi>Caninius Gallus,</hi> a <hi>Quindecemvir,</hi> would have done the like, he was reproved by <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi> for deviating from the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome obſerved by the Romans, and put in
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:98140:13"/>mind what <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> had before done.
<note place="margin">Tacit. Ann. lib. 6. p. 149. Edit. Antw.</note> But I confeſs, upon the beſt ſearch I have been able to make, I cannot find any Law or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Inhibition againſt the reading of ſuch Books as were either not burnt, or not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Capitol; neither indeed could there be; for what the Romans had being now but Tranſcripts, why might not any man have recourſe to the Originals, as well as the Senate? and indeed how could <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Virgil</hi> make uſe of things out of their Books (which were never lookt into but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on weighty and great occaſions) except they had received them from ſome other Copies;
<note place="margin">See the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe p.</note> the curioſity of the Romans extending only unto thoſe in the cuſtody of the <hi>Quindecem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viri,</hi> to which they only gave credit, and puniſhed the divulging, not by any new Law, but by that of parricide, which they infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted upon <hi>Atilius</hi> before mentioned. This is made more evident,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Harum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Sibyllarum carmina &amp; fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runtur &amp; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentur, praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Cumeae.</hi> Lactan. lib. 1. p. 35. &amp; 36. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Xiph p. 230. 25. in Tiber.</note> as well by the Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Lactantius,</hi> who tells you many of their Books were frequently had in his time, as by another, to wit, by <hi>Dio Nicaeus,</hi> as I find it in <hi>Xiphilinus.</hi> In the time of <hi>Tiberius</hi> there went abroad a Propheſie ſaid to be in the Sibylline Books, in theſe words; That after 900 years a civil diſſention ſhould embroil the Romans, and a Sibaritick madneſs. This <hi>Tiberius</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make appear to be falſe, though he were much troubled at it;
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:98140:14"/>and <hi>Nero</hi> after his time finding the peoples troubles not allayed, he told them thoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were not to be found, but inſtead of them they uſed to recite this, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. The laſt that ſhould reign of the Family of <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſhould be the killer of his Mother: But in all this trouble, and endeavours to ſatisfie the people, I find no man queſtioned for reading, or divulging this matter, which undoubtedly would have been done had there been any general inhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or that the <hi>Quindecemvirs</hi> had been found faulty in their truſt:
<note place="margin">See the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, pag.</note> Neither durſt <hi>Origen</hi> have avowed the reading and owning them againſt <hi>Celſus,</hi> whence the Chriſtians were called Sibylliſts: Nor yet <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> himſelf, had there been a general Law upon pain of death not to read them: We cannot, muſt not believe Chriſtians ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal of their lives, or the Heathens ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful, not to have made uſe of it againſt them. The words of <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> are theſe, after he had upbraided them with their prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to read the Books of <hi>Hidaſpes,</hi> the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylls,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> In Apologet.</note> and Prophets, he addes: We do not only poſſeſs them without fear, but as you ſee, offer them to your view. Which words muſt neceſſarily be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to what is before ſaid; for it is notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly known, that till <hi>Stilico</hi> burnt the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol the ſecond time, about the Reign of <hi>Honorius,</hi> which was about 395 years after
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:98140:14"/>Chriſt, the Sibylline Books were kept with the ſame care; and undoubtedly all breach of the Law would have been ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, of which in truth there was none but that upon which <hi>Atilius</hi> was puniſhed, which was that of a parricide in betraying his Countrey, and therefore could not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to others, in whom no truſt was repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. But becauſe I find in this particular va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of opinions, <hi>Baronius</hi> contending the inhibition concerned only the Chriſtians, with whom agrees Biſhop <hi>Montacute in ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. p.</hi> 154, 155. <hi>Iſaac Caſaubon,</hi> and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of the foregoing Treatiſe think the prohibition concerned all promiſcuouſly; I ſhall forbear any determination in this thing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Objections made by</hi> Iſaac Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaubon <hi>againſt their Writings are conſidered, and anſwered.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAving gone thus far, and laid down theſe things as preliminary to what I ſhall farther ſay, I come now to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the moſt material Objections that have been hitherto offered againſt their Writings;
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:98140:15"/>and in this Chapter inſiſt chiefly upon thoſe urged by <hi>Iſaac Caſaubon</hi> (as learned certainly as any adverſary they have had) and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined by others. But I deſire firſt to inform the Reader, that I hold it no way incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on me to juſtifie all things in thoſe Books, as they are now extant with us, to be free from all corruption; (what perhaps will be hard to maintain of any Book very ancient) but will believe it fully ſufficient for the matter I have in hand, if I ſhall ſhew that thoſe places inſiſted on by the Fathers in their Diſputations againſt the Heathens have no marks of calumny that can be juſtly laid upon them, and therefore very adequate to that end for which they were produced by the Author of the foregoing Treatiſe.</p>
            <p>Yet ſhall I farther ſhew <hi>ex abundanti,</hi> that the moſt improbable things are ſo far from being demonſtratively falſe, that they may be true, notwithſtanding thoſe many Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that <hi>D. Blundel,</hi> and others, have heap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together to weaken them, and through their ſides wound thoſe holy men, who for nigh 500 years made uſe of their Teſtimony againſt the Enemies of Chriſtianity. I wiſh I could not gueſs at the reaſon of it, and why <hi>D. Blundel</hi> hath been ſo curious to rake into the aſhes of thoſe holy departed Saints that now reſt in glory, and enumerate their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes, in which I dare boldly affirm he is oftner deceived then they: Nor can I believe any judicious Reader will be led away with
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:98140:15"/>that Paralogiſme in which he ſpends his whole ſecond Chapter,
<note place="margin">See Blundel de les Sibylles, cap. 2.</note> and much of his Book: The Fathers were deceived in other things, therefore in this. Some things are falſe in the Sibylline Writings, therefore nothing is true. Whereas he could not but ſee that the Argument lies as fair on the other ſide: The Fathers in many other things were not deceived, therefore not in this; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a particular wherein for the ſpace of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 150 years (for it is ſo much, or neer it, from <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> to <hi>Conſtantine</hi>) they made it their buſineſs to examine the truth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as peradventure in ſome few other things through the fluency of their tongue, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uberancy of Rhetorick, they might let fall that which makes us ſee they ſtill retained the frailties of men, and had not the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Angels. Nay <hi>D. Blundel</hi> himſelf, when it can any way be drawn to ſerve his turn, is not ſo hard hearted toward the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writers, that he will not allow the moſt ſuſpected of them, <hi>Hermas, Papias,</hi> and others, a more candid and benigne ſuffrage, as 'tis well obſerved by the Learned D. <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> in his defence of <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the Reader will be pleaſed to pardon this ſhort, digreſſion, I ſhall now come to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Objections. The firſt inſiſted upon by <hi>Caſaubon,</hi> is the clearneſs of them: His words are, (having before made uſe of thoſe Texts that call the Doctrine of Chriſtianity a Myſtery) Theſe and the like Teſtimonies
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:98140:16"/>of the holy Scriptures, and the like,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Haec ſacrae Scripturae teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, &amp; bis ſimilia, quî ſtare poſſunt, ſi verum eſt, pleraque, &amp; ea quidem praecipua doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae Chriſtianae myſteria, etiam ante Moſem gentibus fuiſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſita.</hi> Caſaub. Excer. 1. ad ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par. ann. Bar. fo. 67. Edit. Genev. 1655.</note> how can they ſtand toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if it be true that theſe, and the chief Myſteries of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine, were before <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> propounded to the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>Though in anſwer to this I might tell you, that if ſome of the Sibylline Writings have that antiquity I have already touch'd, and ſhall have farther occaſion to ſpeak of; and that thoſe of them that are ſo, have thoſe clear revelations of the Myſteries of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, it was before it had pleaſed God to ſeparate the Jewiſh Nation as a peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to himſelf, but that then all the world made but one Church, governed and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Precepts they had received from <hi>Noah;</hi> and ſo the ſame reaſon to propound thoſe Myſteries to them before <hi>Moſes,</hi> as there was after to the Jewiſh Nation alone: Yet I ſhall chuſe to give you my anſwer in the words of <hi>Caſtalio</hi> in an Epiſtle of his to <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Muſaeus, Anno</hi> 1546. as I find it related by <hi>Simſon, in Diſquiſit. de Sibyllis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are ſome (ſaith he) to whom theſe (Sibylline) Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings ſeem too open,
<note place="margin">Sunt nonnulli, inquit, quibus haec Oracula (Sibyllina) nimis aperta videantur, ideoque ficta putent ab aliquo Chriſtiano ad pelliciendos Gentiles, &amp; ad Chriſtianis gratificandum.— Qui autem nimis aperta pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant faciunt arroganter, ſanè qui Deo vaticinandi modum praeſcribant, quaſi non ei libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſit apertè, obſcurè, apud Gentiles, apud Judaeos ſuo ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitratu praedicaere, aut quaſi non extent in ſacris quoque li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris praedictiones quaedam cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſimae.—Sed fateamur ſanè Sibyllina Oracula eſſe clariora: Nonne quae Gentilibus de Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto praedicta ſunt clariora eſſe oportuit, quòd Moſe, &amp; caete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra diſciplina carebant, quae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ad Chriſti lumen praeluceret, ut quod hîc decrat id Oraculorum claritate compenſaretur? — Quanquam non debemu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Oracula ex eâ quae nunc eſt luce existimare: Nam quae nobis poſt res g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtas notiſſima ſunt, ea cùm futura praedicerentur crant obſcuriſſima. Si quis ea finixiſſet, profectò obſcuriora de induſtria feciſſet, ut ante rem geſtam ſcripta, &amp; his ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia viderentur quae ſunt in ſacrit literis.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore think them feigned by ſome Chriſtian to allure the Gentiles, and gratifie the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.—But they which think them ſo deal too arrogantly,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:98140:16"/>who preſcribe unto God in what manner he muſt prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, as if it were not free to him according to his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to foretell things to come clearly, obſcurely, to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, to the Jews; or as if ſome moſt cleer predictions were not extant in the Scriptures.— Yet ſhould we grant that the Sibylline Oracles are more clear, ought not the revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Gentiles of Chriſt to be ſo, who were deſtitute both of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the reſt of the Jewiſh Diſcipline, which might to them have been as a light to lighten them to Chriſt, that ſo what was otherwiſe wanting might be recompenſed to them by the perſpicuity of the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles themſelves?—Neither ought we to take eſtimate of them from that light that now ſhines amongſt us: For what is to us moſt notable who live after the things fulfilled, might to them to whom they were foretold as future be moſt obſcure. If any man had feigned them, certainly he would on purpoſe have made them more dark, that they might have ſeemed to have been written before the thing accompliſhed, and have more reſembled thoſe of the Holy Scriptures. Thus far he.</p>
            <pb n="184" facs="tcp:98140:17"/>
            <p> But I ask, Were they indeed ſo clear? What means <hi>Lactantius</hi> then, that tells you, They are confuſed and mingled ſo together, that though they were many,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Et ſunt ſingularum ſinguli libri, qui quia Sibyllae nomine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribuntur, unius eſſe creduntur, ſuntque confuſi; nec diſcerni ac ſuum cuique aſſignari poteſt.</hi> Lact. lib. 1. fol. 36, 37. Ed. Hack. 1660.</note> yet they ſeem the works of one body, and are ſo that every ones proper work cannot be aſſigned. And <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copius</hi> in his firſt book of the Gothick Wars ſaith, That they tell not all from the beginning, nor obſerve any harmony or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in their diſcourſe;
<note place="margin">—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. —<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Proc. bel. Got. lib. 1.</note>—and that for that reaſon 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any man whatſoever to underſtand them before the thing foretold is accompliſhed: To which may be added, that we are in all likelyhood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to thoſe that gathered together and ſet in order what we now have, for their plainneſs, who have joyned to the ſame time and place things that ſeemed to them of like nature, which might at ſeveral times, and perhaps by ſeveral perſons diſtant enough in time, be delivered. Furthermore, things as clear have not been underſtood. That of <hi>Balaam,</hi> quoted by the Author of the foregoing Treatiſe. That of <hi>Iſaiah, A Virgin ſhall conceive a ſon, and his name ſhall be called</hi> Immanuel; extreamly clear in the literal ſence, and yet not underſtood by the Jews when foretold, nor believed, when ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled.
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:98140:17"/>If the Sibyll names her Name, the Prophet names his, and leaves out hers, and both name the Town <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> though the Scripture indeed do it in another place. Mr. <hi>Howel</hi> tells you of an Oracle that ſaid,
<note place="margin">Howel Inſtit. Hiſt. p. 787.</note> A Temple dedicated to <hi>Bacchus</hi> ſhould ſtand <hi>donec Virgo peperit,</hi> till a Virgin ſhould have brought forth; upon which the Heathen cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led that Temple eternal, becauſe they deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it impoſſible for a Virgin to conceive; and the thing not underſtood, though true in the literal ſence, and fulfilled at the preaching of our Saviour.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Objection inſiſted on by <hi>Iſaac Caſaubon,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> is drawn from the practiſe of the Primitive times, who, as he tells us, were wont to eſteem it as a great atchievement among themſelves, if they could, by their own figments and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious lies help out the truth,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Poſtremo illud me vehementur movet; quòd videam primis Eccleſiae temporibus quam plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimos extitiſſe, qui facinus pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marium judicabant caeleſtem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem figmentis ſuis ire ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutum: quo facilius nova illa doctrina a gentium ſapientibus admitteretur: Officioſa haec mendacia vocabant bono finc excogitata.</hi> Caſaub. excer. 1. ad app. ann. Bar. p. 67. Ed. Gen.</note> and make the new Doctrine with more eaſe to be received hy the Gentiles; from which fountain he ſuppoſes have proceeded a great number of books under the Apoſtles, and other ſpecious names, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I deny not but ſome ſpurious things have been anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently vented in the Church, as you may ſee in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and others, to what end done I will not now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, which might by obſcurely, and appear ſome years, perhaps ages after, when the cheat
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:98140:18"/>could not ſo eaſily be diſcerned: but that the Fathers ſhould in their diſputations againſt the heathens inſiſt upon what they knew was falſe money, and make themſelves guilty by pious frauds and officious lies, of putting ſo great an abuſe upon the world, is a thing ſo far from the piety and ſimplicity of that age, that I wiſh I could as eaſily wipe out with a ſpunge this injury to their perſons, as I can honour the Memory of that Learned Divine from whoſe pen they have unadviſedly dropt. Nay,
<note place="margin">Mont. Analect. Excer. 4. p. 130.</note> I think I may, with my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> challenge any man to produce one example of Apoſtle or Apoſtolick man guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſuch a falſhood: It became not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Piety to go about to deceive the world; and we find them upon all occaſions ready to expoſe their perſons to the fire, their necks to the Ax, rather than deny a truth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought not to believe this of them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being ſuppoſed to have happened in that Age woen Miracles were not ceaſed, (as is well obſerved by the Author of the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Treatiſe) and ſo they could not be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Chriſtianity would be ſupported by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter means than their pious frauds or officious lies.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="187" facs="tcp:98140:18"/>
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The ſecond and third Chapter of</hi> David Blundell <hi>conſidered, and the Objections anſwered.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN this Chapter I ſhall chiefly examine the Objections made by <hi>David Blundel</hi> againſt the authority of the Sibylline Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, in his ſecond and third Chapter. Part of which is ſpent (after a ſhort commendation of <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>) in enumerating his miſtakes, that from them he might lay ſome colourable ground that he was likewiſe overſeen in what he ſaid of the Sibylls: He ſpares not to tell you, That 'twil be hard to find in all antiquity a more notable miſtake than that of <hi>Juſtin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Il ſeroit malaiſe d'en trouver dans toute la ſuite des temps, un plus illuſtre que celuy du meſconte de S. Juſtin perſonage recommendable s'il en fait jam ais;—Tous ces avantages ont pu le relever par deſſus le commun; mais ils ne l'ont pa empesche de ſe laiſſer abuſer par de conteurs, &amp;c. pag.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.</note> a perſon as worthy of commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as any other hath been: and after the interpoſition of fome few lines touching his learning and virtue, adds, That though theſe advantages have raiſed him above the ordinary rate of men, yet have not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him from permitting himſelf to be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by liars. I ſhould have believed ſo much confidence would have produced ſo great
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:98140:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:98140:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="188" facs="tcp:98140:20"/>Reaſons, that what he laid down was true, that no indifferent Reader ought to have any juſt cauſe to doubt of it; but I find he urges nothing, or very little, for the confirmation of what he ſaith, more than his own conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. The firſt miſtake he alledgeth in the Father, is, That he takes the Statue of <hi>Semo Sangus,</hi> one of the idol Gods of the <hi>Sabines,</hi> to be that of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends was erected at <hi>Rome;</hi> and that he doth this before the Heathens themſelves, with ſo much confidence, that it is very clear he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved what he wrote to be very true: That it is not ſo, <hi>David Blundell</hi> offers no reaſon at all, nor refers himſelf to any other book, wherein he might before have proved it; ſo that for this we have only his conjecture, for ought appears to me: and we have <hi>Cyrillus Hieroſolymitanus</hi> agreeing with <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> That he ſo far deceived the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Cyr. Catecheſi ſexta. Simſon. Anno Chriſti, 67.</note> that <hi>Claudius</hi> erected a Statue for him. That <hi>Nero</hi> was exceedingly, among all other Vices, adicted to that of Conjuration, and Magick, Dr. <hi>Simſon</hi> will tell you out of <hi>Pliny;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not unlikely that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain high honours at <hi>Rome,</hi> till ſuch time as pretending to fly, and being carried up into the air by the Divel, he was brought down head long by the Prayers of St <hi>Peter,</hi> and St <hi>Paul,</hi> who were then at <hi>Rome,</hi> as you may find in the place before alledged.</p>
            <pb n="189" facs="tcp:98140:20"/>
            <p> It is well obſerved by Mr. <hi>Howel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Howel Inſtit. Hiſt. fol. 91.</note> that the Ancients had in great veneration ſuch perſons as were founders of their Kingdoms, and would give them the Names of <hi>Saturn, Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Apollo,</hi> and the like, to whom in the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe times, they gave oftentimes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine honours.
<note place="margin">Lil. Giral. Synt. deor. p. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Lilius Giraldus</hi> will informe you, ſuch as theſe, a kind of Semi-gods, like the tutelary Saints now adays, St <hi>George,</hi> St <hi>James,</hi> St <hi>Andrew,</hi> and the like, were called <hi>Semones,</hi> whom they held not worthy of heaven, for their want of merit, nor would allow them to be earthly, for the reverence they bare their Memory, in reſpect of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours received from them: ſuch, I take it, were the ancient <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Demons, or Heroes, and as Mr. <hi>Mead</hi> thinks,
<note place="margin">Mead, Apoſtacy of the latter times.</note> in his Apoſtacy of the latter times; the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed againſt by St <hi>Paul,</hi> was that doctrine of giving honour to Daemons, or Semigods. That the Sabines had ſuch a one called <hi>Semo Sangus,</hi> (whom ſome take to be <hi>Hercules</hi>) <hi>Lactantius,</hi> among others, who calls him <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> others <hi>Xanthus,</hi> others <hi>Sanctus,</hi> will tell you.
<note place="margin">Lil. Giral. Synt. p. 67. Dion. Halicar. p. 113. l. 2.</note> You may ſee in the ſame <hi>Lilius Giral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> farther, that from him the word <hi>Sancire</hi> to enact, had its Original, from the agreement made between them and the Romans, after the rape of the Sabine women, which you may read of in <hi>Florus.</hi> That there was a Monument or Inſcription of this Oath kept in the Temple of <hi>Jupiter Piſtius,
<note place="margin">Dio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Halicar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 4 p. 257. l. 7.</note> Dionyſius Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licarnaſſaeus</hi> will inform us. That there was
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:98140:21"/>likewiſe an ancient Inſcription, <hi>Sancto Sanco Sermoni Deo Fidio Sacrum,</hi> the Annotator upon <hi>Lactantius</hi> will aſſure you out of <hi>Fulvius <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lact. fol. 82.</note> which in all probability was ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and the form of the Oath mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before out of <hi>Halicarnaſſaeus,</hi> underneath it: But that there ever was any Statue erected of him, kept at <hi>Rome,</hi> is more then I can any way diſcover; (as <hi>Ciril</hi> informs there was of <hi>Simon Magus</hi>) and much unlike, if any had been, that it ſhould continue ſo long as from the time of the war of the <hi>Sabines,</hi> till <hi>Juſtin</hi> the Martyr.</p>
            <p>The next is, concerning the remains of the Cells in <hi>Pharos,</hi> near <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where the 72 Tranſlators of the Hebrew Bible, by the appointment of <hi>Ptolomey,</hi> was performed. This Fiction, he tells us, St <hi>Jerome</hi> derides, who had been himſelf upon the place; and therefore <hi>Juſtin</hi> the Martyr (who was likewiſe an eye witneſs of what he writes) muſt be deceived. But why we are bound rather to believe St <hi>Jerome</hi>'s eyes than <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>'s, with whom <hi>Irenaeus</hi> and many others agree, as <hi>David Blundel</hi> himſelf confeſſes, I ſee not; eſpecially ſince both may be true, there being ſo many years between him and St <hi>Jerome,</hi> that there might be no tracts of that in St <hi>Jeromes</hi> time, which was viſible enough in St <hi>Juſtin</hi>'s. You may ſee at large in Mr <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories Opuſcula,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Opuſ. diſ. of the 70. inter. 19. pag.</note> the opinion of St <hi>Jerome</hi> diſproved; neither ſee I any reaſon to believe (nor doth <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> affirm it) any thing
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:98140:21"/>of that miraculous agreement without alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of any word, as ſome have feigned in their tranſlation: Notwithſtanding it ſhould be allowed that there were little Cloſets in which they made their Tranſlations apart, which were afterward compared, and ſhew'd the King. Yet will Mr. <hi>Gregory</hi> tell you,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Greg. Opuſ. of the</hi> 70 <hi>Inter. pag.</hi> 7.</note> that the other miraculous way of the ſtory may be taken upon the greateſt truſt of Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But theſe hitherto have been but light velitations, or rather handſome inſinuations by <hi>D. Blundel</hi> to gain the favourable attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Readers; that, after he had thus weakened the authority of the Fathers in theſe light things, he might with more eaſe perſwade his Readers they were to blame in preater. We ſhall now in the next place come to conſider his more weighty Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who hath brought together what I have ever found in any other Author to have been alledged againſt thoſe Writings of the Sibylls, with much improvement of his own. In the examination of them I ſhall not ſtrictly tye my ſelf to his order, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them after my own method, that I may, as much as I can, avoid the repetition of the ſame things.</p>
            <p>His firſt and main Objection is drawn from the inconſiſtency and contradiction of the Oracles themſelves:
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>1</label>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Blondel, p.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;c. Opſopae. in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat.</hi>
               </note> For one of them vaunts her ſelf to be the daughter in Law of <hi>Noah,</hi> to have been ſhut up in the Ark, to have been of his blood, guilty of fornication, adultery,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:98140:22"/>nay, if <hi>Opſopaeus</hi> conjecture rightly, of inceſt with her Father, when as theſe Oracles, not extant but in Greek, which was not ſpoken till after the flood, manifeſtly diſcover the impoſture: Nay ſhe that pretends to have liv'd before the flood, by her own confeſſion lived 1500 years after. The places referred to are theſe that follow. Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before of the flood,
<note place="margin">—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Ora. lib. 1. p. 183.</note> ſhe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes the great joy ſhe had to have eſcaped ſo eminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death. The next place referred to is in the third Book, where after ſhe had told you ſhe had come out of <hi>Babylon</hi> in <hi>Aſſyria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 283. <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 360. <hi>in fine.</hi>
               </note> that ſhe ws to prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie againſt <hi>Greece,</hi> and that they ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count her of another Countrey, to wit of <hi>Erithre,</hi> others the daughter of <hi>Circe</hi> and <hi>Gnoſtus,</hi> &amp;c. She after the interpoſition of a few lines ſaith ſhe was of the bloud, and daughter in Law of <hi>Noah;</hi> and in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Book, where the words are faulty, and very obſcure, gives colour to <hi>Opſopaeus</hi> his conjecture of inceſt with her Father.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 260.</note> The third, and laſt place is in the third Book, where ſhe tells you 'twas 1500 years ſince the beginning of the Graecian Monarchy; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Author muſt live after that time.</p>
            <p>Before I come to give a particular anſwer to each member of this Objection,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I deſire it may be firſt remembred, what I have touch'd before in the fourth Chapter, that it is no way reaſonable to believe that we have
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:98140:22"/>every thing in that book now extant ſet down in that order, and time in which they were delivered by the true Authors, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times confounded, and intermixed one with another; ſo that if it can be evidenced that ſome one of theſe Sibylls might have lived before the flood, it no way invalidates their authority, that ſome things may be put together by the compoſer, or gatherer of theſe Oracles as the works of one and the ſame perſon, which indeed were the predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of perſons very different one from another both in age and time.</p>
            <p>That there were predictions of the flood by many others beſide <hi>Noab, Beroſus</hi> will tell you, if we believe his authority, as in that I think we ſafely may; That many preached, propheſied,
<note place="margin">Beroſ. de tempor. ante diluv. lib. 1. p. 48. Edit. Antw. 1552. <hi>Tum multi praedicabant &amp; vatici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabantur, &amp; lapidibus excide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant de eâ quae ventura erat orbis perditione,</hi> &amp;c.</note> nay graved in ſtone the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction that was to come upon the earth, though they were deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and not believed. Neither ſeems it to me improbable, that many pious, and holy men lived about that time, though they were by God brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their reſt before this general deluge of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter happened, to which <hi>Noab</hi> and his Family only ſurvived. The ſame <hi>Beroſus</hi> tells you, that the Chaldeans kept Records of many things before the flood; tells you of <hi>Enos</hi> a Town of Gyants; with him agrees <hi>Martini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the Jeſuite in his Hiſtory of <hi>China</hi> printed at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> 1659. where he relates many
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:98140:23"/>things out of the Records of that Kingdom before the flood; and truly, that our prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors were never Maſters of ſome pieces of Antiquity, of which we have now no foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps left, is to believe them leſs careful to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after knowledge then we are, or leſs curious to tranſmit it to poſterity; for how is it poſſible that <hi>Noah</hi> himſelf, and thoſe of his generation that ſucceeded him, ſhould either not tell, or their children not enquire what was done in the old world, and alſo leave ſome memorials of it to ſucceeding times, till the Graecians (whoſe Language quickly grew almoſt univerſal) having robb'd the Phenicians, and Chaldeans of their Learning, robb'd us alſo of a great part of that knowledge we might otherwiſe have been partakers of, by clouding it under Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thological tales and fictions of their own, by which means they eclipſed Learning, which they made ſhew to promote, out of their pride to make the world beholding to them as the firſt Inventors of all knowledge in it, and not letting us know out of what foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain they drew it. From this and another artifice frequent in very ancient times, of calling by the names of <hi>Saturn, Apollo, Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and the like, perſons whom for ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert they had a mind to honour with thoſe appellations, came ſo great confuſion in ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: Where we ſhall find ſometime that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to a later perſon which was true of ſome Predeceſſor of his of the ſame name.
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:98140:23"/>Something to this purpoſe you may ſee in <hi>Xenophon,</hi> and <hi>Bochartus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zenop. de aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocis in princi pio.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bochart. in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>b de S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rm. Phaent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sar Walt. Raw: lib. Sect.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bochar. cap.</hi> 12. <hi>pag.</hi> 432.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lil Gir. Synt. Deor. p.</hi> 39<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 32. <hi>pag.</hi> 214 39.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Onup. de Sibyl.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> neither were it hard to give many examples of it, were it proper in this place to do it.</p>
            <p>The uſe I ſhall make of it is, that from hence I may induce you to believe it very poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that a Sibyl might be before the flood, and ſhut up with <hi>Noah;</hi> for if it be true, as <hi>Bochartus</hi> thinks, that <hi>Vulcan,</hi> and <hi>Tubal Cain</hi> were the ſame. <hi>Lilius Giraldus</hi> among others will tell you, that <hi>Apollo</hi> (who, as <hi>Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius</hi> ſaith, taught <hi>Sibylla Delphica</hi> the art of Divination; and that ſhe liv'd long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Wars of <hi>Troy</hi>) was the Son of <hi>Vu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> or <hi>Tubal Cain;</hi> and ſo it might very well be that the Son of <hi>Tubal Cain</hi> might converſe with a Daughter in Law of <hi>Noah,</hi> which might alſo live a good while after the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Tongues, eſpecially ſince <hi>Sem</hi> is by ſome thought (I am ſure might) to have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Simp. Chron. p.</hi> 19. <hi>Anno M.</hi> 1988.</note> who was born 18 years before the death of <hi>Noah,</hi> as Dr. <hi>Simp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſaith.</p>
            <p>But we need not go ſo high; for if <hi>Noah</hi> were <hi>Saturn,</hi> his three ſons, <hi>Sem, Cham,</hi> and <hi>Japhet,</hi> were <hi>Jupiter, Neptune,</hi> and <hi>Pluto,</hi> as is proved in the ſecond Chapter; as alſo out of <hi>Pauſanias,</hi> that the ancienteſt Sibyll was the daughter of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Lamiah,</hi> who was the daughter of <hi>Neptune,</hi> that is to ſay of <hi>Cham,</hi> by his Niece who was <hi>Japhets</hi> daughter; I ſee no reaſon why that art of Divination, which <hi>Pauſanias</hi> tells you was in
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:98140:24"/>the daughter, might not be known both to her mother as well as father, who we are ſure were ſhut up in the Ark with <hi>Noah,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince the ſame <hi>Pauſanias</hi> tells you, that Oracles were delivered long before, as an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently as the earth it ſelf, as you may ſee in the ſecond Chapter of this Diſcourſe. I ſhall farther out of the ſame Author ſhew, that Divination was common between <hi>Neptune</hi> (that is <hi>Japhet</hi>) and the earth; that before any Temple was made, the earth her ſelf uſed to pronounce them: Nay the ſame <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanias</hi> yet farther tells you of certain Verſes mentioned by thoſe of <hi>Delos,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Pauſan. in Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cicis, pag. 327.</note> in which one of them names her ſelf ſometime <hi>Herophile,</hi> ſometime the wife, ſometime ſiſter, ſometime daughter of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo.</hi> Poſſibly theſe Hymnes were the ſame with thoſe called <hi>Eumolpia,</hi> written by one <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaeus,</hi> as you have it, <hi>pag.</hi> 320. of the ſame Author. Sometime you will find <hi>Daphne</hi> called the preſident of the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, ſometime <hi>Phemonoe,</hi> ſometime of a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of a Temple built by <hi>Vulcan,</hi> and all this confeſſedly before the Trojan Wars, but no time when; which certainly was becauſe by reaſon of its antiquity they could not: And I confeſs in the relation of <hi>Pauſanias</hi> there is a little uncertainty, and obſcurity; but I think I may with as much probability (upon what you have heard) affirm ſome of
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:98140:24"/>his ſort of Diviners were before the flood, as <hi>D. Blundel</hi> can demonſtrate the contrary; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſince the foiſting in this particular could not ſerve for any other end then to make the whole book be rejected, which not conducing to the intereſt of any party, either Chriſtian or Heathen (who both allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them) cannot well be ſuppoſed. Nay if Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> be not miſtaken, who ſaith, that very learned men were of that opinion, the names of <hi>Saturn, Jupiter,</hi> and the like, were in uſe from the very Creation; <hi>Adam</hi> being the firſt <hi>Saturn, Cain</hi> the firſt <hi>Jupiter,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Rawl. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. And ſince Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children are oft called by the names of ſons and daughters, no man can aſſuredly affirm that one of <hi>Cains</hi> poſterity was not daughter in Law to <hi>Noah;</hi> ſo that although I allow that <hi>D. Blundel</hi> might have reaſon to ſuſpect this place as ſpurious, yet all he ſaith amounts not to a demonſtration that it is ſo; and therefore all the Books not to be rejected up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the only account of this place. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion that ſhe was guilty of the knowledge of ſtrange beds, rather makes for, then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth of them; for it is like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſhe was polluted with the ſins of the old world, having lived in it; the confeſſion that ſhe was ſo, argues rather her repentance then anothers falſifying that place. That they are extant only in Greek, which at the flood was not ſpoken, may receive a double anſwer, either that they were made ſo by the Graeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:98140:25"/>after they came into their hands; or that the Author, as ſhe well might, lived both before, and after the Confuſion of Tongues. The laſt part of this Objection is, that ſhe, whoever ſhe be, mentions 1500 years to have paſſed of the Graecian Monarchy, which could not be true, had ſhe lived at the time of the flood.</p>
            <p>In the anſwer to this Objection, I muſt needs remember what I find runs through his whole Book, and I ſhall repeat no more; that whatever he finds in theſe Oracles that cannot agree with her that calls her ſelf the daughter in Law of <hi>Noah,</hi> are therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true; as if there never had been but one Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byl, the contrary to which is proved in the ſecond Chapter; ſo that it might be true that there was one in the time of <hi>Neah,</hi> and yet this the prediction of another. But let us a little more narrowly look into his reaſon, and we ſhall find it no way conſequent, that becauſe the word there uſed is in a Tenſe that ſignifies the time paſt, therefore the thing it ſelf muſt be alſo paſt at the time of the delivery thereof; whereas nothing is more frequent in Propheſies, and Viſions, then to uſe the time preſent, or paſt, for what is to come. Now the truth of the thing is no more then this. The Author of thoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, whoever ſhe was, after a ſharp reproof of the Graecians for their Idolatry, hath theſe words.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> That the Graecians had reigned fifteen hundred
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:98140:25"/>years,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. lib. 3. p. 260.</note> who firſt led men unto wickedneſs: And after tells them of the wrath of God, and that then upon the feeling of it they ſhould begin to ſeek him: And laſtly, ſpeaks of the growth and flouriſhing of Chriſtianity; in all which it will be evident many things are foretold which were not at that time paſt; and indeed they import no more then that 1500 years after the beginning of the Graeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Monarchy Chriſtianity ſhould flouriſh: Now whether this happened true in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent is impoſſible to judge, ſince Hiſtorians cannot agree when to begin the Graecian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; nor is it to be known what period in Chriſtianity is pointed at by theſe Verſes.</p>
            <p>Another Objection he inſiſts upon not much unlike the former;
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>2</label> to wit, that this (ſtill the ſame <hi>Sibylla</hi>) that calls her ſelf daughter in Law of <hi>Noah,</hi> is by <hi>Juſtin</hi> the Martyr called the daughter of <hi>Beroſus,</hi> who wrote the Chaldean Hiſtory. The words are theſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. In Pareneſi ad Gent. p. 30. Edit. Rob. Step. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> You may eaſily learn in part the right way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God from the ancient <hi>Sibylla.</hi> This Sibyll they ſay came out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> being the daughter of <hi>Beroſus</hi> that wrote the Chaldean Hiſtory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſoon after hath theſe words in the ſame page. Of this Sibyll <hi>Plato</hi> (among many other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of his time that mention
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:98140:26"/>her) ſpeaks of in <hi>Phaedro;</hi> nay whom himſelf afterward calls the moſt ancient Sibyll. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to this Teſtimony: Though the words are indeed ſo in the Father, yet it carries ſo great a wound in its own breaſt, that we may eaſily ſuſpect ſome foul play hath been uſed toward him, and this place corrupted; for how could <hi>Plato</hi> remember her that was daughter to <hi>Beroſus</hi> that writ the Chaldean Hiſtory, who dedicated his books to <hi>Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus Soter</hi> (as <hi>D. Blundel</hi> himſelf confeſſeth out of <hi>Tatian</hi>) when as <hi>Plato</hi> dyed in the year of the world 3656,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Armagh. ann. fol</hi> 198. <hi>and</hi> 344 <hi>of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Edit.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Antiochus Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Seleucus</hi> his Father, and was the third King of <hi>Syria</hi> after the death of <hi>Alexander,</hi> began not his Reign till the year of the world 3724, in which year <hi>Seleucus</hi> dyed; ſo that there are 68 years between the death of <hi>Plato,</hi> and the firſt year of the Reign of <hi>Antiochus;</hi> therefore in the moſt modeſt account <hi>Beroſus</hi> muſt be above 100 years old when <hi>Antiochus</hi> came to the Crown, or elſe <hi>Plato</hi> could not mention his daughter as a Sibyll; for we cannot reaſonably believe ſhe was inſpired before twenty, or him mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried before the like age; ſo that at the death of <hi>Plato</hi> he muſt be 40 years old, and have lived to 108, and then have ſpirit, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs enough to write Hiſtory; except we will ſuppoſe he kept it by him during the whole time of <hi>Alexander,</hi> (who we know was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways an encourager of Learning) and thoſe
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:98140:26"/>that ſucceeded him to dedicate it to <hi>Antic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> a man not at all in repute to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with <hi>Alexander,</hi> which is very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable. This miſtake then muſt either be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to ſome inadvertency in the Father, or, which I rather think, ſome later Writer intending to explain the words, corrupted the ſence by foiſting in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Writer of the Chaldaean Hiſtory;</hi> the words running very clear without that addition. The cauſe of this miſtake I think proceeded from their not conſidering that there might be more then one <hi>Beroſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pauſan. p.</hi> 328. <hi>in Phocicis.</hi>
               </note> Now <hi>Pauſanias</hi> tells you that ſhe that ſucceeded <hi>Demo</hi> was by the Jews called <hi>Sabba;</hi> that <hi>Sabba</hi> was the daughter of <hi>Beroſus</hi> and <hi>Erimanthe</hi> according to ſome; others that this <hi>Sabba</hi> was called <hi>Sibylla Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonica;</hi> others <hi>Aegyptiaca:</hi> Much incertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty there is in what age to place her; proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly it hath come from that miſtake in <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> which I believe miſled <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> who makes the ſame perſon mentioned by <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> (whom he calls <hi>Sambethe Noe</hi>) to be the eighth in number, but by <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> and others is reckoned the firſt; in my opinion with more reaſon; for ſhe mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Juſtin</hi> is called the firſt and very anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Sibyll, and muſt certainly point at one more ancient then the age of <hi>Alexander.</hi> But whoever ſhe was, and when ever ſhe lived, whether in <hi>Solomons</hi> time, as you have it in the end of the ſecond Chapter out of <hi>Cedre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi>
               <pb n="202" facs="tcp:98140:27"/>but denyed by <hi>Collius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Collius de ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabus Pagan. pars</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>pa.</hi> 190, 191.</note> or much anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enter, certainly ſhe could not be daughter to that <hi>Beroſus</hi> who writ the Chaldaean Hiſtory, for the reaſons before alledged: And of the ſame opinion I ſince find was <hi>Montacute</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Norwich</hi> in his Excercitations upon <hi>Baronius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Montac. in ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. p.</hi> 153.</note>
            </p>
            <p>A third Objection,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>3</label> is, That the name of <hi>Adam</hi> is, by the Author of the firſt book of the Sibylline works,
<note place="margin">D. Blund. p. 7. <hi>Il eſt penſe que l'impoſteur qui a voulu ſe ſignaler par. la feint d'une ſi grang antiquite s' eſt monſtre fort neut</hi> 1. <hi>en derivant Adam de</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>comme ſi c'eſtoit un mot d'extraction Grecque.</hi>
               </note> derived from the greek work <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as if it were a word of Greek extraction, and alſo denoted from the Hebrew the four Quarters of the World, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Eaſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Orac. Sibyl. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 216.</note> Weſt, North,</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> whereas his Name in the Hebrew and Chaldean Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage conſiſts only of three letters.</p>
            <p>He that conſiders who it was (even God himſelf) that impoſed the Name upon our firſt Father,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> and farther that the Name of Jew and Greek ſhould divide the whole world, the Greek being a common name, comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Gentiles,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Paul. Romans cap.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 12.</note> as appears by the firſt and tenth of the <hi>Romans,</hi> with many other places. He (I ſay) that conſiders this, will not, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf, believe it ſtrange that the ſame appellation might be ſignificant in more Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages then one, though not then in being; that he that was not created a man only, but a King over all the Earth and the creatures thereon, ſhould have a Name that reached
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:98140:27"/>over all the Quarters thereof, ſhews rather the providence of God, who by it would let us ſee, that not only Monarchical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was the firſt, and therefore beſt, but by himſelf inſtated upon <hi>Adam,</hi> ſtamped and imprinted in his very name, in which the point under <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſupplieth the third letter, which he pretends is wanting.</p>
            <p>But what can be anſwered to <hi>David Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels</hi> inadvertency, if after all this the book, as to that part of the objection which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the derivation of the name of <hi>Adam</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, warrant no ſuch thing, but quite contrary; the words are theſe; Having firſt told you of the encreaſing of mankind after that of their wars and wickedneſs, ſhe tells you, that God took them away by death; That <hi>Hades</hi> received them; That indeed they called it <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> from <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </q>
               </note> becauſe he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taſted of death went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther firſt; for which reaſon all men that are born of the earth are ſaid to go down to the houſes of <hi>Hades.</hi> What can be imagined more contrary than this to the affirmation of <hi>David Blundel;</hi> he tells you, <hi>Adam</hi> took his name from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when the book warrants, that the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> had its deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from <hi>Adam,</hi> not <hi>Adam</hi> from it. Of this opinion likewiſe is Mr. <hi>Sanford,</hi> in his book <hi>De deſcenſu Chriſti ad inferos,</hi> publiſhed and
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:98140:28"/>perfected after his death by <hi>Robert Parker;</hi> he tells you, <hi>pag.</hi> 8. — <hi>luce clarius eſt,</hi> Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mah <hi>primum in</hi> Hadam <hi>deinde in</hi> Haden <hi>abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe;</hi> and <hi>pag.</hi> 39, &amp; 40. diſputes it, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever go about to derive it from a Greek foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain are miſtaken.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>4. &amp; 5.</label> A fourth and fifth Objection he raiſeth from the numbers of the names reſulting from the name of GOD and of JESUS,
<note place="margin">
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>n</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>70</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>400</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>200</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell> </cell>
                        <cell>888</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </note> the one conſiſting of 1697. the other of 888. the number of 1697. not agreeing to any name of God, and the other only to the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Sibyl. Orac. pag.</hi> 184. <hi>in fine, &amp; pag.</hi> 171.</p>
            <p>Though for anſwer to that part of this Objection which concerns the ineffable name of God,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I might refer you to the conjectures of ſeveral men; (<hi>Leo Suavius</hi> who contends it agrees to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of <hi>Morellus</hi> who ſaith it agrees to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Johannes Auratus</hi> who tells you <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is underſtood; of <hi>Brenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> who expounds it by the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: All which you may ſee gathered together by <hi>Opſopaeus</hi> in his Notes upon the place;
<note place="margin">Opſop. p. 11, 12.</note> and laſtly to <hi>D. Blundels</hi> own conceit, which you may ſee <hi>pag.</hi> 7.)
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Yet I rather chuſe to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my own ignorance in not knowing whence to draw it, then to condemn the Book becauſe I do not: Only let me obſerve, that he ſuſpects the Book becauſe the firſt Aenigme is obſcure, and paſſeth the ſame cenſure upon it, becauſe 'tis intelligible in the ſecond.</p>
            <pb n="205" facs="tcp:98140:28"/>
            <p> I confeſs, I think the ſecond Aenigme agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the name of Jeſus, conſiſting of the number 888. may have much in it of myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſince it is compoſed of the firſt number which conſtitutes the firſt cubical or ſolid fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure that doth <hi>complere locum,</hi> fill a place, as the Mathematicians will tell you, diſpoſed <hi>per monadas, decadas,</hi> and <hi>hecatontadas,</hi> to ſhew that the foundation of our Salvation by Jeſus is ſolid, that the Author and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher thereof is in all things perfect and compleat; whereas the name 666 given in Scripture to Antichriſt is not at all ſo. Much more to this purpoſe might be added, but this touch ſhall ſuffice.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, He accuſes them of falſhood,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>6</label> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they tell you that <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue but 948 years, which were deduced from the number contained in the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>I find by this Objection,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> that though <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid Blundel</hi> was a very good Grecian, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by all his Books, yet he here rather choſe to make uſe of the Latine Tranſlation which ſerv'd his turn, whereas the Greek warrants no ſuch thing. The words are, That <hi>Rome</hi> ſhould fill up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of 948 years,
<note place="margin">
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                  </q> 
                  <bibl>Lib. 8. p. 375.</bibl>
               </note> at which time ſhe having filled up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of her name, a ſad por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or violent fate ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach her: For that is the ſence of the words, which war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:98140:29"/>no ſuch thing as a final end of the City; and in truth in my judgment are not unlike thoſe before quoted out of <hi>Xiphilinus</hi> the Epitomizer of <hi>Dion,</hi> that after 900 years a ſtrange diſſention and madneſs ſhould di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide and embroil them, which cauſed ſo much trouble in <hi>Tiberius</hi> his time, as you may ſee in the fourth Chapter foregoing: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that both he and <hi>Nero</hi> endeavoured to appeaſe the fears of the people, who were much perplexed with the apprehenſion of it: So that you may ſee they harped much upon 900 years, as if ſome fatal accident ſhould then happen: Upon which <hi>Opſopaeus</hi> thinks that theſe Verſes were by ſome later Writer inſerted in imitation of thoſe former, becauſe no ſiniſter accident happened then to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Which time fell out about the ſecond or third year of <hi>Severus,</hi> as <hi>D. Blundel,</hi> and <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopaeus</hi> both agree, and is eaſily proved.</p>
            <p>That no ſolid Argument can be raiſed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways out of the Numeral Letters of a word, to determine by it the fate or downfall of any City or Kingdom, I eaſily grant; but that nothing at all can at any time be gathered from thence, is to condemn all the Cabaliſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Learning of the Jews, and bring them upon our ears, who, as we all know, lay of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes much weight upon ſuch kind of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentations: But let us ſee if nothing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table happened about that time. By that ſad portion which ſhould then happen to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty might well be underſtood the growth of
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:98140:29"/>Chriſtianity, which at laſt ſhould bring a final ruine to Heatheniſme, as indeed it did. Now we find at this very time <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> two Heathen Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, and converted Chriſtians, great Champions for the Faith as ever it had, flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, and writ in the Defence of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Chriſtianity. About four years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Apollonius</hi> a moſt Learned Philoſopher, and Chriſtian, gave an account of his Faith before the Senate, and was beheaded for it, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> in his Chronology, and <hi>Helvicus</hi> both have it. Theſe things then happening might well be as ſo many warning pieces pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaging the downfall of Heatheniſme, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly muſt of neceſſity produce much civil diſſention, and partaking on all hands, and could not but be lookt upon as a ſad and unfortunate accident to the City, which might well be called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Beſide, between the years 900 and 948 lived <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and ſuffered Martyrdome; <hi>Polycarp</hi> appeared at <hi>Rome</hi> about the difference of Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; <hi>Eleutherius</hi> and <hi>Victor</hi> Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> then flouriſhed; <hi>Athenagoras</hi> writ an Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for the Chriſtians, as you may ſee in <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicus</hi> his Chronology: All which had, if in nothing elſe, yet in their very ſufferings, a kind of Victory over Paganiſme, and a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Rome,</hi> which afterward fell in that ſence, when the Emperour became Chriſtian, about 300 years after the Birth of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            <pb n="208" facs="tcp:98140:30"/>
            <p> A ſeventh Objection is,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>7</label> That the Author of that part of the Sibylline Oracles makes <hi>Ararat,</hi> where the Ark reſted, to be in <hi>Phry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia:</hi> The words are in the firſt Book, p. 180.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And after the interpoſition of two Verſes, follows
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l> 
                  <bibl>Sib. Orac. p. 180.</bibl>
               </q> There is, ſaith ſhe, upon the Continent of black <hi>Phrygia</hi> a long and arduous Mountain called <hi>Ararat,</hi> within which the Springs of the River <hi>Marſyas</hi> ariſe, upon whoſe high top, when the waters abated, the Ark reſted.</p>
            <p>By theſe words nothing more can be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily collected,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> then that <hi>Ararat</hi> is upon the ſame Continent with <hi>Phrygia;</hi> for ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies the Continent as it is diſtinguiſhed from an Iſland. <hi>Phrygia</hi> is indeed in the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer <hi>Aſia</hi> bounded with <hi>Cappadocia</hi> on the Eaſt part of the Mountain, <hi>Taurus</hi> on the South, <hi>Troas</hi> on the Weſt, and <hi>Galatia</hi> on the North; and if <hi>Ararat</hi> be in <hi>Armenia,</hi> the Weſt part of <hi>Armenia</hi> borders upon <hi>Cappadocia;</hi> ſo that, for ought appears to the contrary, if the Ark reſted in <hi>Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nia,</hi> as ſome hold, the Springs of the River <hi>Marſvas</hi> that runs through <hi>Phrygia</hi> might well enough ariſe there, the Mountain <hi>Ararat</hi> extending very far in length. Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> places <hi>Armenia</hi> the leſs in <hi>Natolia,</hi> or the leſſer <hi>Aſia,</hi>
               <pb n="209" facs="tcp:98140:30"/>makes the Mountain <hi>Ararat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rawleigh, cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Sect.</hi> 10 <hi>pag.</hi> 108.</note> now called <hi>Tau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> extend very far, as you may ſee in the Map annexed to the ſeventh Chapter, <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.</p>
            <p>But let us take it with <hi>David Blundel</hi> in the moſt rigid ſenſe that the words of the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylls do indeed import, that the Ark did reſt in <hi>Phrygia</hi> near the Springs of the River <hi>Marſyas,</hi> is he ſo aſſured of the place of its reſt, that he dares from this falſity conclude all the Oracles ſpurious.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bocbart. Geog. Sac. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 15. <hi>&amp; Seq.</hi>
               </note> The Learned <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chartus</hi> in his <hi>Geograp. Sac. p.</hi> 18. tells you the common opinion is, that <hi>Ararat</hi> is <hi>Armenia,</hi> but leaves the place of its reſting very doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, inclines to the Gordiaean Hills, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed lye in <hi>Armenia</hi> the great, but no part of the Mountain <hi>Ararat,</hi> but a good way di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Beroſ. p.</hi> 55. <hi>Edi. Antwerp.</hi> 1552.</note> 
               <hi>Annius</hi> the Fryar in his Notes upon <hi>Beroſus</hi> labours much to prove it reſted upon the Caſpian Mountains, which ſeparate <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia</hi> from the upper <hi>Media,</hi> and do equally belong to both.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rawleigh, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. <hi>p.</hi> 108.</note> Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> makes that long ridge of Mountains which extend from <hi>Phrygia</hi> to the Confines of <hi>Scythia intra Imaum,</hi> to be by <hi>Moſes</hi> called <hi>Ararat,</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours by many, and weighty reaſons to prove that the Ark reſted upon that part of <hi>Ararat</hi> near <hi>Caucaſus</hi> that borders upon <hi>Scythia intra Imaum,</hi> as you may ſee in the Map by him annexed of thoſe parts, agreeing in that his opinion with <hi>Goropius Becanus,</hi> and our Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> with them both.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heylin, Geog. p.</hi> 8, 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Whilſt then we remain under ſo great an uncertainty touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this matter, what can be reaſonably con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:98140:31"/>to the overthrow of the Sibylline Books from this medium? Some light we might have, did we certainly know that part of the world where it was built, whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick and bulk, with the great burthen of all the creatures, and proviſion for their nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for a years time at leaſt kept within it, would not ſuffer to float very far, but only as the current of the waters and wind might drive it. But where ever it reſted, the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture tells you they journeyed from the Eaſt to the plains of <hi>Shinaar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> where they built the Tower of <hi>Babel,</hi> and the confuſion of Tongues happened. This reaſon, among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, induced Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> as dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and judicious a Writer as any other, to place the reſting of the Ark in that part he doth, and makes <hi>Nimrod</hi> to have a very long journey from thence, being the Eaſt part to the place where <hi>Babylon</hi> ſtood: Whereas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe if you place it upon the Gordaean Hills, as <hi>Bochartus,</hi> or in <hi>Phrygia</hi> as <hi>Sibylla, Babylon</hi> lying South or South-Eaſt to both theſe places, they could not be ſaid to jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from, but toward the Eaſt, that travelled from thoſe parts to <hi>Babylon.</hi> To ſolve this difficulty,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bochart. Geog. Sac p.</hi> 35. <hi>ca.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Bochartus</hi> tells you his own conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and ſeems to diſlike others; that the Aſſyrians called all that part of their Empire which lay on the other ſide of the River <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris,</hi> the Eaſtern part, all on this ſide the Weſt; and ſo would make the Mountains of <hi>Ararat</hi> belong to the Eaſt, becauſe they were
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:98140:31"/>in that Tract that lay on the other ſide of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gris:</hi> Whereas if this diviſion of the Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Empire were not as well his conjecture as the other part of it, and that in truth there was no ſuch diviſion in uſe among the Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians in the time of <hi>Moſes;</hi> yet is it no more then if one ſhould ſay, that the Inhabitants of <hi>England</hi> travelling into <hi>Virginia</hi> could be ſaid to come out of the Weſt, becauſe they were heretofore part of the Weſtern Empire. <hi>Jacobus Capillus</hi> makes the Hebrew word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Kedem</hi> to ſignifie a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and ſaith;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Noae poſteritas ab Armenia montibus progreſſa fuerat in cam regionem quae poſtea dicta eſt <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Kedem à Kedma no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſimo Iſmaelis filio.</hi> Bochart. pag. 35.</note> the poſterity of <hi>Noah</hi> came from the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Ararat</hi> to that Region which was afterward called <hi>K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem</hi> from <hi>Kedma</hi> the youngeſt Son of <hi>Iſmael.</hi> Others will tell you, that <hi>Kedem</hi> ſignifies as well the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as the Eaſt, and that the ſame word is ſo uſed <hi>Habak. chap.</hi> 1.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Habak. chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>Art not thou <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> from everlaſting,</hi> or from the beginning? So <hi>Gen.</hi> 2. the Chaldee Paraphraſe renders the ſame word in that ſenſe; ſo doth <hi>Theodoſion,</hi> St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> and ſome others. <hi>And the Lord planted a garden of Paradiſe from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Pſal.</hi> 68. we render the words ſo.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.33.</note> 
               <hi>To him that rideth upon the Heaven of Heavens which were of old,</hi> or from the beginning. With this Tranſlation agree <hi>Montanus</hi> his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlineary, and the Chaldee Paraphraſe, as you may ſee in <hi>Bib. Polyglot.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bib. Polyglot.</note> If this verſion may be allowed, as undoubtedly the words
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:98140:32"/>will bear it, then is that difficulty wholly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, and the words import no more, then that after the Ark had reſted, and the Inhabitants of the earth began to enlarge their bounds, the beginning of their pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grination was toward the Land of <hi>Shinaar;</hi> and thus is the word rendered in this very place by the Chaldee Paraphraſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bib. Poly. Gen.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> as you may ſee in <hi>Bib. Poly.</hi> But let us ſee if we may diſcover any farther light out of the Sibyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Writing it ſelf. Admitting the words before quoted do neceſſarily imply, that <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> where the Ark reſted, doth indeed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thoſe Oracles, lye in <hi>Phrygia,</hi> then muſt it be in a place not far from the Springs of the River <hi>Marſyas:</hi> Now the River <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyas</hi> riſes about <hi>Celaene</hi> neer the River <hi>Maean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> as appears by <hi>Xenophon, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Anabas.</hi> The Court of the great King is in <hi>Celaene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Xenoph. lib. 1. Anab.</note> fortified near, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Springs of the River <hi>Marſyas,</hi> beneath the Caſtle, which runs likewiſe through the City, and empties it ſelf into <hi>Maeander.</hi> With whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree <hi>Livy, Strabo,</hi> and others. Then probably there may be a miſtake in the Tranſcriber,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Liv. lib.</hi> 38.</note> and the verſe ought to run, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. the Letters χ and μ not being ſo very unlike, but that the ſame miſtake hath been before made in that word, as <hi>Bochartus,</hi> and before him, <hi>Caſaubon</hi> have obſerved. Now the ſame <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chartus</hi>
               <pb n="213" facs="tcp:98140:32"/>will tell you, that <hi>Apamia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bochart. Geog Sac. p.</hi> 16, 17.</note> long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter built by <hi>Antiochus Soter,</hi> and whither the Inhabitants of <hi>Celaene</hi> tranſplanted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, was called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies an Ark, perhaps from the tradition that the Ark of <hi>Noah</hi> reſted there, as likely as from any other reaſon, in which let the Reader be judge: Sure I am what I have ſaid is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough in anſwer to <hi>D. Blundel,</hi> whoſe only exception is, that <hi>Ararat</hi> is made to lye in <hi>Phrygia,</hi> when himſelf, were he alive, could not determine neither what that Mountain is now called, nor where it lyes. But I muſt not diſſemble what the learned <hi>Bochartus</hi> far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther addes out of <hi>Plutarch,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bochart. p.</hi> 17. <hi>lib.</hi> 1.</note> that the River <hi>Marſyas</hi> had its name from <hi>Marſyas</hi> the Son of <hi>Midas,</hi> which was many ages after the flood; and ſo that ſhe that was with <hi>Noah</hi> could not remember it. To which I ſhall ſay, this ſeems to be only a conjecture of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and the Son of <hi>Midas</hi> might as well receive his name from the River, as that from him; except you like better to believe this verſe foiſted in by ſome late Writer, who remembring that <hi>Celaene</hi> was called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from the tradition of the Arks reſting there, thought by this means to explain the Oracle, but indeed corrupted it: A misfortune like to it I have before ſhewed you happened to the text of <hi>Juſtin Martyr:</hi> For if that verſe be left out, the ſenſe of the Oracle is no more, then that in the Continent of black <hi>Phrygia</hi> there is a long and arduous Mountain called
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:98140:33"/>
               <hi>Ararat,</hi> upon whoſe high top the Ark reſted.</p>
            <p>But <hi>D.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Blond. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 9</note> Blundel</hi> will not thus give us over, but tells us, that this very perſon diſcovers her ſelf to be a Chriſtian, and that ſhe compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this her Rapſodie between the years after Chriſt 138 and 151. that is between the time of the death of <hi>Adrian,</hi> and that part of the Reign of <hi>Antoninus,</hi> when <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented his Apology. The words referred to are theſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.—Lib. 8. p. 403.</note> We therefore that are ſprung from the holy, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly generation of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By which words, ſaith he, ſhe evidently manifeſts her ſelf to have lived after Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Though I might accommodate many an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to this place, and tell you, that all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever that have been ſaved were regenerated by Chriſt, whether exhibited or to be exhibited, and that future things are often declared as paſt: Yet ſince it is not my task to juſtifie all things in thoſe eight Books to be as ancient as the flood, but only to ſhew 'tis poſſible ſome things therein might, I ſhall not contend with him about it; ſo as on his part it might be as equally conceded, that there were more Sibylls then one, which I find him very hard to be induced to, as you may ſee in his ſeventeenth Chapter at the end,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Blond cap.</hi> 17. <hi>p.</hi> 78.</note> where he ſaith, all the eight Books which we have were written by one and the ſame hand; I confeſs very pertinently to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, had he proved it, but contrary to the
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:98140:33"/>ſence of all the world before him; except by writing he underſtand compoſing, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in order the works of many perſons, which probably might be the labour of one and the ſame perſon, according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Eaſtern Countries at this day (as I am informed by a Learned Divine that hath travelled in thoſe parts) where their manner is to gather together the wiſe ſayings of their Progenitors, who ever they were, without any order, or conſideration of time, or other circumſtance, and ſo tranſmit them to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, indeed as a Rapſody, or disjointed things that have no neceſſary connexion or dependance one upon another, and yet all, or much of them very true. That theſe Writings of the Sibylls may have had their ſhare in this fate, as to ſome particulars therein, I think probable enough, but that will not ſerve to impugne the authority of them all.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>8</label> Another Objection urged by <hi>D. Blundel</hi> againſt theſe Books is taken from their direct contradiction of the Holy Scripture;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 7.11. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 8.14.</note> for whereas <hi>Moſes</hi> tells you that <hi>Noah</hi> continued in the Ark from the 17th day of the ſecond moneth to the 27th day of the ſecond moneth following,
<note place="margin">
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <bibl>Sibyl. Orac. lib. 1. p. 183.</bibl>
               </note> the Authour of this work plainly ſaith, that <hi>Noah</hi> went out of the Ark the eighth perſon, after he had fulfilled forty and one days in the waters, according to the will of God.</p>
            <pb n="216" facs="tcp:98140:34"/>
            <p> If this learned man had as much endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to have gathered Arguments for the aſſerting the truth of the Sibylline Predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> as he was curious and diligent to heap up all imaginable matter that could be found out any way to impugne their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, he might from this place have found out as well reaſon to believe them true, as by it conclude their falſhood; for he could not but ſee that the Hiſtory of the flood is told almoſt directly like to that related by <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Geneſis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                  </lg> 
                  <bibl>&amp;c. Sibyl. Orac. lib. 1. pag. 179.</bibl>
               </note> The opening the flood-gates and cataracts of Heaven, of his opening the roof of the Ark, of his great fear, of the endleſs extent of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, of the earths being cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and drowned by them ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny days, and of the terrible face of the Heavens during that time. She then tells you the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the firſt ſending out of the Dove, her return; then the ſending her out the ſecond time, her return with an Olive branch in her mouth: After this the ſending forth the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, who returned not: And before the firſt ſending forth the Dove, tells you of ſome remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the air after the earth had been watered with the rain many days: And after this and
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:98140:34"/>the firſt return of the Dove, his remaining in the Ark more days: And much more to that purpoſe, all which could not probably be performed in the ſpace of 40 or 41 days, in which time 'tis ſcarce imaginable either how or from whence ſo great a bulk of water could come, as was ſufficient to cover the whole globe of the earth ſo high, as to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough above the higheſt mountain upon the face of it, that all the Inhabitants might be drowned, had not the immediate hand, and power of God intervened to effect it. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that no Impoſtor whatſoever, except he had been more fooliſh then falſe, would have tranſcribed a ſtory out of <hi>Moſes</hi> with circumſtances comprehending ſome length of time in their performance, and at laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict his own relation in a matter which lay directly before his eyes, and impoſſible not to be detected. We may therefore with more reaſon believe this relation not to have been taken out of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but rather to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded out of the mouth of her that was in the Ark with <hi>Noah,</hi> which being no way prophetical but hiſtorical, may admit of a greater latitude, and lead us to conclude the Writer, whoever ſhe was, pitched upon ſome conſiderable, or notable period of 41 days, in which they were in the greateſt danger. Let us therefore ſee if we can any way diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover when this was. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 7.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 11.</note>
               <pb n="218" facs="tcp:98140:35"/>That on the ſeventeenth day of the ſecond moneth, when <hi>Noah</hi> and all his Family with the creatures were in the Ark, and that the Lord had ſhut up the door upon them, that the fountains of the deep were broken up, and the cataracts of Heaven opened, and that it rained upon the earth by the ſpace of forty days and forty nights. This certainly was the period aimed at by the Sibyll (who might well call it 41 days, reckoning the day they all, or ſome of them, entered into the Ark before the rain fell, for one, and <hi>Moſes</hi> only reckoning the time whilſt the rain was falling) during which time they might well be ſaid to be ſhut up by the Lord, as well for their defence againſt the impetuoſity of the weather and waves, which ſhook the ribs of their wooden habitation, as the violence might have been offered to it both by men and beaſts, before the waters had force e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to raiſe it out of their reach, or depth enough to drown them: All which time, if we believe the Eaſtern Traditions, <hi>Noah</hi> and his Sons kept a ſolemn Faſt, taking meat but once a day, as I find it in <hi>Gregories Opuſcula, p.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Catena veterum praecipuè Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entalium in Pentateuchum. Arabicè M.S. in orchivis Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliot. Bodl.</note> 28. out of the <hi>Catena Arabica:</hi> And <hi>Noah</hi> was the firſt who made the 40 days holy, or inſtituted the Quadrageſimal Faſt in the Ark. The words thus explained are fully conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with what is recorded in Scripture; the many days mentioned by the Sibyll compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending all that time definitively ſet down by <hi>Moſes</hi> till their going out; the 41 contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:98140:35"/>only thoſe in which they faſted, and were in continual horror and fear of death, which they might truly ſay to have fulfilled in the water, being environed with it both above their head, and beneath the ſoles of their feet. So that this Argument is ſo far from ſtanding <hi>D. Blundel</hi> in any ſtead, that it much ſerves to confirm, not weaken their authority.</p>
            <p>In the ninth place he urges,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>9</label> that they coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the fable of the Titans, as if it were true; the opinion of the Chiliaſts as to the re-building of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That much concerning the Titans or Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, as their ſtory is related by Poets,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> may be ſabulous, I ſhall eaſily grant; but that what is urged by the Sibylls concerning them is alſo ſo, <hi>D. Blundel</hi> hath not proved. They are mentioned in ſeveral places in the Sibyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Writings: Firſt in the firſt Book.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <bibl>Lib. 1. p. 184.</bibl>
               <p>Again,</p>
               <l>—<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <bibl>Lib. 2. p. 204.</bibl>
               <p>Again,</p>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <bibl>Lib. 3. p. 232.</bibl>
            </q>
            <pb n="220" facs="tcp:98140:36"/>
            <p> From all which places there is no more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, then that God would at laſt execut judgment upon thoſe Titans or Giants whom the flood had devoured, who were a wicked generation. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.16. <hi>The man that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth out of the way of underſtanding ſhall remain in the Congregation of the dead,</hi> as we render it, in the Congregation of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaim</hi> in the Original,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Mead in Diatrib. upon Prov.</hi> 21.16.</note> which word by the Septuagint is always rendred Giants, Titans, or the like: So that I ſee nothing to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt in their Writings, or to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them as fabulous for calling the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the old world Titans.</p>
            <p>That which he calls the Haereſie of the Chiliaſts he could not be ignorant had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved learned Supporters both in ancient and modern times: Whether what ever hath been hitherto urged in their defence be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed, remains yet <hi>ſub judice;</hi> certainly thoſe which believe the Jews ſhall yet once more be graffed into their own Olive-tree, will not think it unreaſonable that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> may be again as famous in the profeſſion of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, as it hath formerly been of Juda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D.
<label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>10</label> Blundel</hi> farther objects, That thoſe Books make <hi>Adrian</hi> the Roman Emperour that ſucceeded <hi>Trajan,</hi> by whom he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted, as ſome ſay, to have ſtrangled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which was in no ſort true.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adrian</hi> was not indeed ſtrangled,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>, as the words in the Sibylline Oracles import, which are as follow.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="221" facs="tcp:98140:36"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <bibl>Sibyl. Orac. lib. 8. p. 367.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>The ſence of them is, that when fifteen Kings had ſubjected the world to themſelves from the Eaſt to the Weſt, one ſhould ariſe wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a white helmet, having a name almoſt of the Sea, overlooking the world with his polluted feet, that gathered and ſpent much money, skilful, or making uſe of all the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Magick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> After the interpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of two or three verſes, ſhe ſaith, then ſhall be a lamentable time, becauſe he periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a halter.</p>
            <p>This perſon, though no body is particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly named, is commonly taken to be <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> both becauſe he is the fifteenth from <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar,</hi> his name ſeems to reſemble the Adriatick Sea, and that he made uſe of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick ſpells for the curing his diſeaſe, of which <hi>Xiphilinus</hi> tells you he was once by the help of Magick recovered,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Xiphil. Epit. Dion. p.</hi> 360. <hi>lin.</hi> 29.</note> but after fell again into the ſame, whereof he miſerably dyed, after he had in vain implored death from the hands of his ſervants, but could find none to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford it him.</p>
            <p>The difficulty of this place is eaſily recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled, by admitting an eaſie miſtake in the
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:98140:37"/>Tranſcriber, by putting an [n] in the place of a [b]; for if we read the Verſe thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 'tis then true according to the ſtory, that a drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſhould deſtroy him; for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies a drop of water or a tear, and in poeſie may, eſpecially in aenignatical or prophetical ſpeeches, denote a dropſie.</p>
            <p>Some other Objections <hi>D. Blundel</hi> hath gathered together touching ſome Geogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical miſtakes, ſome doubts concerning <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> concerning Antichriſt, and ſuch like, to which ſatisfaction might be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fily given; but I rather forbear, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that no man that is in ſome meaſure ſatisfied with the anſwers given already to the moſt material Objections, of which I have pretermitted none, but will eaſily ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie himſelf as to the reſt in that Chapter.</p>
            <p>But having gone thus far, and ſeen the ſtrength of <hi>D. Blundel</hi> as an oppoſer, we ſhall in the next Chapter conſider him as an anſwerer, and ſee if in that he ſucceeds any better.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="223" facs="tcp:98140:37"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>The Oppoſition made by</hi> D. Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del <hi>to the Authorities and Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the Ancient Writers in favour of the Sibylline books, and his anſwers to them weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THis Learned Divine, and great Reader of Authors both Chriſtian and Heathen, having left no ſtone unmoved which could any way ſerve his turn to the overthrow of theſe Writings; yet at laſt could not but ſee the Authorities of ſo many Writers of great Antiquity, and for many hundred years together which had decurrently made uſe of the Teſtimonies of the Sibylls for the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their Adverſaries, would ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main like ſo many thorns in his feet, he thought it very neceſſary to ſay ſomething in reply to what had been urged by them. The firſt he takes into conſideration is <hi>Clemens Alenandrinus,</hi> a perſon, he knew, of variety of Learning, inſomuch that ſome part of his Books were called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:98140:38"/>of the ſubjects they handled, and of great antiquity in the Church, having flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed (and written, as 'tis thought) within 160 years,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heloic. Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nol. pa.</hi> 91.</note> or thereabout, after the death of our bleſſed Saviour; and finding that he had in ſundry places mentioned the Sibylls, and their Books, particularly in his firſt Book <hi>Strom.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clem. Alexand. Strom. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 323 <hi>B. Edit. Pariſ.</hi> 1629. <hi>&amp; p.</hi> 304.</note> in which he mentions many of them, and among others <hi>Phemonoe,</hi> whom he affirms to have lived twenty ſeven years before <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus,</hi> who was one of the Captains in the expedition of the <hi>Argonauts</hi> againſt <hi>Jaſon</hi> for the golden Fleece, about the year from the Creation, according to <hi>D. Simpſon,</hi> 2743. (according to <hi>Helvicus</hi> not ſo much) who by the way tells you,
<note place="margin">Simpſon in an.</note> that what before was read 27, ought to be 107, as the ſame Author had before noted in the ſame Book; who had alſo before mentioned another ancienter then this <hi>Phemonoe,</hi> another later, namely <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylla Erythre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> with others, whereas <hi>D. Blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> contends there was but one and the ſame perſon Author of all the Sibylline Books now extant much after Chriſt: Nay farther, that he was not ignorant that <hi>Pauſanias</hi> mentions the daughter of <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Lamia</hi> long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the building of <hi>Delphos,</hi> in which place <hi>Phemonoe</hi> was perhaps one of the firſt that gave out Oracles, though long after the firſt Sibyll: And had farther obſerved, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny verſes now extant in the Books we have, and other paſſages therein, were mentioned in Heathen as well as Chriſtian Authors: That
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:98140:38"/>
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> who was not only a Chriſtian, and ſo by his profeſſion bound to ſpeak truth; but an Emperour, and ſo in a capacity by his power to examine all Records, and other means by which the truth might be diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, had not only aſſerted their authority, but made it evident that both <hi>Virgil</hi> and <hi>Tully</hi> had ſeen and made uſe of ſome paſſages now in thoſe Books we have: He had great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe, that ſome of his Readers would lay more weight upon the judgment of ſo many grave Writers, then to be led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by his bare ſuſpition.</p>
            <p>The paſſage he firſt lays hold on is in <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Alexandrinus,</hi> in his ſixth Book, in theſe words.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Lib. 6. Strom. p. 636.</note> Over and above the preaching of S. <hi>Peter, Paul</hi> the Apoſtle ſaith, Take unto your ſelves the Graecian Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; read <hi>Sibylla</hi> how ſhe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly declares one God, and the things that are to come.</p>
            <p>That which he replies to this place is very fit to be ſet down in his own words, though they are ſomewhat long. They ſhall give me pardon (by their leave) if I ſay they accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulate one ill upon another;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mais il me pardonneront (s'il leur plaiſt) ſi je dis que ils ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulent mal ſur mal; car s'il ya de la faute a ſouſcrire (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me S. Juſtin) a une fauſſete que l'on n'a peu recognoiſtre, combien doit eſtre odicux le crime de ce faux teſmoign qui (pour tromper Clement Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrin &amp; les autres Chreſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens) a voulu ſouſtenir la ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition des eſcrits Sibyllins, par une pire impoſture, &amp; fein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre que S Paul luy meſme leur avoit concilié de l'authorité par ſa recommendation? Si les bonnes ames ont de la pe ne a ſouffrir que l'on donne en leur preſence les eloges de la pudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te a de louues de bordel, qui d'entre les vrais Chreſtiens pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſupporter que l'on egale aux prophetes de dieu des hypocon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driaques. &amp; a leurs oracles coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtes, des reſveries embaraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſées, &amp; que l'inventeur d'une ſi indigne fourbe, oſe pour la maintenir, produtre l'Apoſtre comme complice de ſon audace ſacrilege? On veut n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ant moins que de ce vaiſſeau d'ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſoient ſorties les paroles rapportées par Clement, &amp; pour ce que rien de tel ne ſe trouve en ſes epistres on ſe figure qu'il les a prononcees en ſes ſermons populairs, come s'il avoit eſte poſsible a celuy qui a ſacrific ſa vie par un glorieux martyre l'an</hi> 65 <hi>de noſtre Seigaeur, de donner ſon approbation a une piece pleine de fautes, &amp; forge de puis l'an</hi> 137, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Blond. des Sibylles, cap. 5. p. 15. &amp; 16.</note> for if it were a fault to give conſent (with S. <hi>Juſtin</hi>) to an untruth which he could not know, how odious ought the fault to be of this falſe witneſs,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:98140:39"/>who (to the end he might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> and the reſt of the Chriſtians) hath ſhew'd himſelf willing to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the ſuppoſition of the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylline Writings by a worſe impoſture, &amp; feigns that S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf had given them autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by his recommendation? If thoſe good ſouls would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing that one in their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſhould commend for cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity the perſons hired in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean houſes, what true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian could endure to hear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualled to the Prophets of God and their Propheſies the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broiled fancies of Hypochon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driacks, and that the Inventor of this ſo unworthy cheat ſhould dare for the maintenance of it to produce the Apoſtle as a Partner of his ſacrilegious boldneſs? Notwithſtanding all this there are that would have theſe words quoted by <hi>Clemens</hi> to have proceeded out of the mouth of this Veſſel of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and becauſe no ſuch thing is found in his Epiſtles, they feign to themſelves that he ſpake them in his Sermons to the people, as if it were poſſible for him who ſacrificed his life by ſo glorious
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:98140:39"/>a Martyrdome 65 years after our Saviour, could give approbation to a piece full of faults, and forged 137 years after.</p>
            <p>I ask firſt who was this falſe witneſs whoſe crime was ſo odious, who was the inventor of that ſo unworthy a cheat; and that durſt make St <hi>Paul</hi> his partner in ſo ſacrilegious a boldnes; and that deceived <hi>Clemens,</hi> and the reſt of the Chriſtians? I am ſure there is nothing extant in their Writings, that tells you that St <hi>Paul</hi> made uſe of them; and I think he did not believe any body ſtood at <hi>Clemens</hi> his elbow to engage him to father that upon St <hi>Paul</hi> which he would not own; ſo that it muſt neceſſarily follow, that <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> himſelf muſt be the perſon guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this cheat, this ſacrilegious boldnes, to deceive both himſelf and other Chriſtians: Certainly <hi>D. Blundel</hi> had too much worth to intend any ſuch calumny to this Writer, or to affix ſo ill language of him; and I obſerve it only to let you ſee how far that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the immoderate drawing of all things to the contrary part, to ſerve their ends, may miſlead wiſe men, after they have eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the defence of any cauſe, though never ſo unjuſt.</p>
            <p>We will now examine what in this Allega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is Argumentative on <hi>David Blundels</hi> part: His deſign is to ſhew theſe eight Books of the Sibylline Writings, to be embroyled fancies, rapſodies proceeding from hypochon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driaques full of faults, and written 137. years
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:98140:40"/>after Chriſt. To do this he tells you <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> urges, That St <hi>Paul</hi> remitts the Gentiles to the Books of one of the Sibylls to prove the unity of the Godhead, and other things to come; but there is no ſuch thing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in St <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtles, that we have; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe Books are ſpurious, falſe, and I know not what elſe. Were he able to prove that St <hi>Paul</hi> never ſaid or wrote any other thing than what we have in thoſe ſew Epiſtles of his, and that little that is related of him in the <hi>Acts,</hi> nothing more would follow than that <hi>Clemens</hi> miſalledged him, nothing at all to the overthrow of the Books, which we know were in the world both in <hi>Tully</hi>'s and <hi>Virgil</hi>'s time, and therefore could not be unknown to St <hi>Paul,</hi> being ſometime in the Court of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> and bred up unto much learning. We know he did upon the like occaſion remember them of the Poems of <hi>Aratus</hi> and <hi>Epimenides,</hi> and why not of the Sibylls? We have reaſon enough to believe <hi>Clemens</hi> might have ſome pieces of St <hi>Paul</hi> which are unknown unto us, the rather ſince we ſee new things are day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcovered; witneſs the firſt Epiſtle of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Romanus</hi> (the genuineneſs of which few doubt, yet) not brought to light till our days; and why the like may not be ſuppoſed of St <hi>Paul,</hi> I ſee not: This is clear, he had a good eſteem of thoſe Writings, and that in his judgment St <hi>Paul</hi> might have made uſe of their authority in that point. Oh, but here is a great deal of clearneſs in theſe Oracles more
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:98140:40"/>than in the Scriptures; therefore St <hi>Paul</hi> could not be the Author of this Allegation. Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the clearneſs of theſe Writings in general, I have ſpoke at large in the fourth Chapter; as to their plainneſs for the proving the Unity of the Godhead, certainly nothing in the world can be more clear than the Scripture in many places; ſo that <hi>D. Blundel,</hi> as to this particular, hath not made his reply good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Clemens</hi> his Authority in any part. I wonder he did not as much find fault with his quotation of the Sermon of St <hi>Peter</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Stromat. p.</hi> 635.</note> where he tells you of the Unity, Incomprehenſible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Inviſibility, of his filling all things, and ſtanding need of nothing, of his making all things by the power of his Word, that is, his Son, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more undoubted truths, but not delivered, at leaſt not all of them, in thoſe words, by St <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in any thing of his now extant. I cannot doubt but could that have been uſeful, he would have heaped it up alſo amongſt <hi>Clemens</hi> his miſtakes, with which he fills up his next Chapter; and, were they all true, would be very little to his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>After this, from the beginning of the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Chapter to the end of the fifteenth, he ſpends his whole time, and as much paper as I have alloted my ſelf to this whole diſcourſe, in ſhewing you the more important miſtakes
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:98140:41"/>in the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> in his eleventh Chapter; then his miſtakes of leſs importance in the fourteenth; the diſcovery and clearing the opinion of <hi>Cicero,</hi> in the twelfth, and of <hi>Virgil</hi> in the thirteenth Chapter; that <hi>Virgil</hi> did not diſguiſe his opinion, is the ſubject of his fifteenth Chapter. Whereas after all this labour and pains, he wholy miſtakes both the deſign and drift, not only of the Emperor, but of all other the Chriſtians that have made uſe of the Sibylline Writings, whoſe aim was not to concern themſelves what was the opinion either of <hi>Tully</hi> touching them, or what <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil</hi> meant in his fourth Eclogue; but whether the words of one do not clearly import that there were Sibylls, and that in their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings were Acroſtiques; and that the words of the other import that which is not appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable to any but our Saviour: Now that this is made good in every particular, is ſo clear, that the very recitation of the words are of themſelves able to confute any man. The words of <hi>Tully,</hi> in his ſecond Book of Divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are theſe. Speaking of the Sibylls. The Poem it ſelf evidently ſhews,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Non eſſe autem illud carmen furentis cum ipſum Poêma de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarat (eſt enim magis artis, &amp; dilig <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiae, quam iucitationis, &amp; motus) tum vero ea quae <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> dicitur cum dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ps exprimis verſus literis ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid connectitur ut in quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Ennianis quae Ennius fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</hi> Cicer. de Divinat. lib 2.</note> that the Verſes are not a mad bodies, (for it ſavours more of Art and diligence, than of ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den motion, or incitation) eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that which is called an Acroſtich, in which, from the firſt letters of every verſe down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, ſomething is framed or
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:98140:41"/>knit together, as it is in ſome of thoſe which <hi>Ennius</hi> hath made. 'Tis clear enough from theſe words that there were Acroſticks, and ſuch as <hi>Ennius</hi> made; but of what ſort thoſe were we cannot know, ſince of him we have nothing left that I know of, but certain frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments gathered together out of all Authors by <hi>Robert Stephen,</hi> and put out by <hi>Henry</hi> his brother: But if we may gueſs at them by thoſe in the Arguments of moſt, if not all the Comoedies of <hi>Plautus,</hi> who was near,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Helvic. Chron. act. ann. mun.</hi> 3712.</note> if not of his time, (for between the birth of <hi>Ennius</hi> and death of <hi>Plautus</hi> are but 60. years, or thereabout, and both before <hi>Tully</hi>) we ſhall find them ſuch as thoſe quoted out of the eighth Book of the Sibylline Oracles, and repeated by <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> ſo that I look upon that in <hi>D. Blundel, pag.</hi> 55. as a fancy; who would have Acroſticks ſo made, that the number of the letters in the firſt Verſe ſhould contain the number of the verſes in the whole Poem, and that the ſecond of the firſt ſhould be the firſt letter of the ſecond verſe, and ſo conſecutively; of which ſort he gives one on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly verſe, as an example, 705 years after Chriſt, and perhaps the only one ever made of that ſort.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lil. Giral. de Poet. Hiſt. Dial.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Lillius Giraldus</hi> tells you of Acroſticks, and Paraſticks, but of none of this ſort; ſo that we have little reaſon to believe thoſe in the Sibylline Oracles were other than what we have. <hi>Dionyſius Halicarnaſſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> tells you, the true Sibylline Writings were diſcovered by the Acroſticks, enough to prove there were ſuch.</p>
            <pb n="232" facs="tcp:98140:42"/>
            <p> Thoſe of <hi>Virgil</hi> are in his fourth Eclogue too long to tranſcribe, and ſuch, that <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> in his Oration <hi>Ad Sanctorum Caetum,</hi> ſpends his nineteenth and twentieth Chapters to ſhew they could not be underſtood of any other but our Saviour, and ſhews there, that thoſe, as well Acroſticks as other Writings of the Sibylls, had been ſeen both by <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>Virgil,</hi> and the Acroſticks tranſlated by <hi>Cicero,</hi> and all this made ſo manifeſt by thoſe that had accurately computed the time, that their teſtimony is beyond exception. Of the ſame opinion is <hi>Lactantius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lact. l.</hi> 5. <hi>de ver. ſap. p.</hi> 400.</note> who tells you, None that hath either read <hi>Cicero</hi> or <hi>Varro</hi> will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve theſe Writings counterfeited by the Chriſtians; out of which theſe teſtimonies had been produced by perſons dead long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the birth of our Saviour. But I had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forgotten that he offers ſome reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Acroſtick mentioned in the Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> becauſe in the Sibylline Books it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, conſiſting of one letter more than the name ought to have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the true writing thereof; whereas <hi>D. Blundel,</hi> who makes this Objection, could not be ignorant that the ancient <hi>Graecians</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the name of <hi>Chriſtus octoſyllabum,</hi> as <hi>Irenaeus</hi> tells him:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iron. li.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 10.</note> And <hi>Valeſius</hi> in his Notes upon <hi>Euſebius,</hi> lately put out at <hi>Paris,</hi> 1659. hath theſe wrods; The ancient <hi>Graeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> accounted the Name of Chriſt to conſiſt of eight ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables (taking ſylable there for
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sance veteres Graeci nomen Chriſti octofyllabum faciebant <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> cum dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> l.</hi> 1. <hi>c</hi> 10.</note>
               <pb n="233" facs="tcp:98140:42"/>a letter) writing Chriſt, <hi>Creiſt,</hi> with a dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thong. I confeſs I find not that particular in <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> in the place quoted, nor remember it in any other; but of this I am ſure to have obſerved in ancient Greek Inſcriptions upon Statues and Pillars,
<note place="margin">Vid. Seldini Marmora Arundeliana.</note> what we now write with a ſingle I, expreſſed by a dipthong, and the like, which is evident in the writing of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Latinus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of Predictions of things to come; and of Divination in general, what ſorts lawfull, what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain. Of</hi> Enthuſiaſme, <hi>the definition of it. Of Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticks, and ſuch of our Time who have pretended to Viſions, and Revelations. The diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between true and fals Prophets: In what rank the Sibylls are to be accounted.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>DAvid Blundel</hi> having urged all the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments he could againſt the Sibylline
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:98140:43"/>Books, now at laſt employs many Chapters touching Enthuſiaſme, the conſideration whereof I ſhal now take in hand, but think it not amiſs in the firſt place to ſpeak ſomething of Predictions in general, and the ſeveral ways by which future events are foretold, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently come to paſs. The firſt is of wiſe and Learned men, who from their Obſervations out of Hiſtory, and comparing the times paſt and preſent, when they ſhall ſee the ſame things come again upon the ſtage of the world that have formerly been, and then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering all circumſtances of agreement, and difference, are able to give a probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, which ſeldome fails, of what is like to come to paſs, which ſort of Predictions are not only lawful, but worthy of much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, and are very frequently conduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the good of Kingdoms, by preventing evils otherwiſe like to come upon them.</p>
            <p>A ſecond ſort is Aſtrological Prediction, wherein the Artiſt undertakes from the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Heavens, and configurations of the Planets, at ſuch a certain moment of time, to foretell future accidents: This Art I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay is unlawful, but I take it to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectural, uncertain, and by ignorant people much abuſed: Strange things are, I confeſs, often foretold, and ſometime prove true, when a skillful Artiſt hath the handling of the matter, but many times are otherwiſe; ſometime from the ignorance of him that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes the judgment, other while from the
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:98140:43"/>influence of ſome of the fix'd ſtars, which being ſeldom taken notice of, may croſs or hinder what would otherwiſe haply have come to paſs; or thirdly, from the want of a ſufficient treaſure of Obſervations, by which judgment ought to be given; the ſame poſture of the Heavens having never twice happened alike in every circumſtance ſince the Creation; and by that means leaving the world deſtitute of ſtable means to judge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſince what can be rationally ſaid in that kind muſt proceed from the comparing of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents which have happened under ſuch and ſuch Configurations, with what are like to be when the ſame fall out again; or, laſtly, from the care of the party himſelf, who may by his own induſtry prevent what his deſtiny from the influence of the Stars would have been, which at moſt do not neceſſitate, but incline, and by the providence and over-ruling pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God are ſometimes diverted.</p>
            <p>A third ſort is a geomantical or terreſtrial Divination, in which from certain voluntary points made by the hand at adventure, certain figures are raiſed; from the four firſt of them called Fathers, are produced other four called daughters; thoſe eight bring forth four grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children, from them come out two Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, from thoſe a Judge, in all twelve, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the twelve Houſes in Aſtrology, and the judgment upon this ſort of Divination not much unlike that of Aſtrology. The ground of this Art and its foundation is laid
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:98140:44"/>upon a falſe ſuppoſition, that the ſoul of man knoweth things to come, but is hindred by the dulneſs of the Organs of the body; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore in the practice of it a great ſedateneſs of mind is required, a freedome from all noiſe that may diſturb it, and ſuch like circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which he that hath a mind to know may find in <hi>Cattan,</hi> Dr. <hi>Floud,</hi> and <hi>H. de Piſis,</hi> who have all written largely upon it. This kind of Divination I take to be idle, vain, and ſuperſtitious, as not built upon any ſtable foundation of Reaſon, or ſupported by any thing but fancy.</p>
            <p>A fourth ſort is by framing certain Figures of ſtone or metal, underneath ſuch Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and placing them either in ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous place of a Town, or ſometime under ground, by which ſtrange things are wrought; theſe are called <hi>Taliſmans,</hi> of which, as alſo the language of the Stars, with an Alphabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Table, and how from that words are framed, which ſhall declare the event of things to come, according to the nature of the Queſtion; <hi>Gaffarel,</hi> a Learned French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, hath largely written in his Book called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nheard of Curioſities;</hi> ſuch they will prove to him that ſpends much time in the ſtudy of them. Other frivolous ways of ſortiledge there are, which I ſhall purpoſely paſs over.</p>
            <p>The next way of Divination I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is Enthuſiaſme, or Illumination; and this is moſt to our purpoſe to treat of; <hi>Heſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> in his Gloſſary interprets it thus: An
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:98140:44"/>Enthuſiaſtick is one that is mad or full of the Spirit.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſme is a ſtupor or horror: Or, Enthuſiaſme is when the whole ſoul is enlightned by God. By which ſeveral interpretations of the word, it may eaſily be gathered, that En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſm may be of ſeveral kinds; ſome natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, or at leaſt proceeding from ſome diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the body, which ariſing from a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral cauſe, it may be ſo called; others come by poſſeſſion or inſpiration of ſome ſpirit ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or bad, which may be well deem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſupernatural. Much conteſt there is whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all Enthuſiaſme be natural, and to that purpoſe the authority of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> is produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, who diſcourſing of the ſeveral paſſions ariſing from drink, love, and the like, or from ſome melancholy heat, tells you the ſtory of one <hi>Maracus</hi> of <hi>Siracuſe,</hi> a Poet, who never made ſo good verſes as when he was made, and immediately before hath theſe words; Many becauſe that heat is near the ſeat of the mind,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Arist. Probl.</hi> 30. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1.</note> are taken with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry frantick and Enthuſiaſtick diſeaſes; from whence they all become Sibylls, Bakides, or inſpired, whereas they become not ſo by any diſeaſe, but a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural temperament. From which words we may obſerve two things. Firſt, That he doth not in this place point at any Sibyll in particular,
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:98140:45"/>of which many had been before his time, but takes Sibylls there for perſons any way inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as the Bakides and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> joyned with them, were ſuppoſed to be: And in the next place, That he muſt (not to contradict him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) take diſeaſe in a different ſence in the ſame place; for in the beginning of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence he tells you, They are taken with many frantick or Enthuſiaſtick diſeaſes, and ſoon after ſaith, They become ſo not from any diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, but a natural craſis or temperaments; in the laſt place therefore he muſt take diſeaſe in that ſtricter notion, for ſuch an affection as ſhakes and weakens the whole frame of the body; in the firſt, for ſuch a diſtemper as drunkenneſs, love, poetical rapture, and the like, ſuch as he calls natural Enthuſiaſme, which will either be its own cure, or vaniſh away with time, the conſtitution being ſound, though the action be altered; but however it will from theſe words of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> follow, that in his ſence much of this kind of illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination proceeded from an exaltation of the mind by ſome ecſtatick operation of the ſoul, and not from any poſſeſſion or inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it by either good or evil ſpirits: And undoubtedly great examples in all ages may be produced out of the Obſervations of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Phyſitians, to this purpoſe, ſome where of have been meer cheats, to gain credit to ſuch as ſhould cure or exorciſe them; others true, or natural, where through ſome melancholy heat, or ſtrong imagination, or laſtly, through
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:98140:45"/>cuſtom and uſe;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Montagnes <hi>Eſſays, Strange effects from the force of imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, in his Chapter upon that ſubject.</hi> Fienus de viri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus imaginatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</note> the perſons affected have brought upon themſelves ſuch a habit of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that their fancy prevailing over their judgment and underſtanding, they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally believed themſelves poſſeſſed with a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Propheſie, and enlightning from God, whereas in truth there was no ſuch thing. I my ſelf have known two examples in Perſons both of this Nation, of good Rank and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; the one a man whom I have often ſeen, and ſometimes heard diſcourſe, but was then too young my ſelf to converſe with him, but am well aſſured he was otherwiſe a very ſober perſon; but in that particular of explaining difficult propheſies, did think himſelf ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly indowed; inſomuch that his confidence ſo far miſled him, that he could no way be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven out of that opinion, That the eleventh Chapter of the ſecond Apocryphal Book of <hi>Eſdras</hi> denoted King <hi>James,</hi> who was the Lion of the North, who plucked at the fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Eagle, which he conceived to be the Emperour: Nay, his confidence in this fancy was ſo great, that after the death of the King, he believed he ſhould riſe again out of his grave to make good his conjecture. The other was a Lady of Noble Rank, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended much to this gift of Propheſie, and having unhappily foretold the death of a great perſon which by chance fell out true, ſhe was mightily puft up with it, and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome of the giddy multitude; ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook to denounce the end of the world,
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:98140:46"/>writ upon the prophecy of <hi>Daniel,</hi> very idly, and at laſt lived to ſee her ſelf deceived in all her vain extravagancies. Theſe two might certainly be reckoned amongſt the Enthuſiaſts of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who laboured under ſome light diſorder of the brain, which diſturbed their judgment as to that particular, though in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matters they were ſober enough; and under the ſame notion muſt I look upon the falſe Prophets, Dreamers, and Quakers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this Age hath been very fertile, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend themſelves endued with an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meaſure of the Spirit of God; firſt dream dreams, then ſee viſions, then expound them after their own imaginations, and would obtrude theſe upon the ignorant mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude as Revelations of God, which are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed no other than the effects of a diſturbed brain, what they foretel rarely coming in any meaſure to paſs, and themſelves never able to confirm their miſſion by any miracle whatſoever, to induce men to believe them Prophets: Some of them are not unlike the Dereviſes or Torlaces in <hi>Turky;</hi> who by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent uſing their bodies to turn round, can at their pleaſure fall into extaſies, in which they pretend to receive meſſages from God, and deceive thoſe that give credit to them; though, to ſpeak truth, the ſad conſequences that have followed from the doctrine of ſome of theſe pretenders to new Lights, may give us good cauſe to believe them to have been led away into theſe extravagancies by the
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:98140:46"/>ſpirit of errour and deluſion, and not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a natural diſturbance of the brain: Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs (as we have great reaſon to ſuſpect) that many of them have been carried on by inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and deſign, by ſuch pretences to deceive others, thereby to compaſs their wicked de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, of which we have ſeen too ſad effects. From this, and much more which might be materially added to this purpoſe, it will be evinced, that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> had much of truth and reaſon in what he ſaid; but becauſe ſome were either cheats, or Hypochondriaque, that therefore all were, and among them the Sibylls, as <hi>D. Blundel</hi> would infer, I can no way be induced to believe; nor doth he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce any reaſon that they were ſo, whereas the very great time between the predictions, and the fulfilling of them ſufficiently evince, that they came from a higher cauſe then a melancholick heat: In which I have ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that between the Propheſie and the time allotted for the adimpletion of it, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom interceded more then a ſcore of years, ſometimes not ſo many moneths. Beſide we find, that as well the Sibylline Predictions as all other Oracles ceaſed at, or ſoon after the preaching of our Saviour, whereas me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholick diſtempers continue ſtill, which to me ſeems a ſtrong argument that they were different in their cauſes. Neither ought the authority of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> too much to ſway us in this thing: I allow him to be one of the greateſt Maſters of reaſon that ever was, but
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:98140:47"/>withal muſt remember, that being contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary with <hi>Plato,</hi> and ſometime his Scholar, but reſolving to ſet up a new Philoſophy dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from that of his Maſter, would not comply with him in that particular in which he deemed him faulty: For it is obſervable, that as <hi>Plato</hi> often ſpeaks of Sibylls Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Revelations, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> mentions none, or very ambiguouſly, reſolving to go a quite contrary way, not medling with any thing of which he was not able to give a probable reaſon. And all others of the Ancients who have denyed the truth of all Oracles or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions whatſoever, except natural, were ſtill of the Sect of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> meer Atheiſts, and conſequently bound by their Sect to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve nothing in this kind but what they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be ſo: For which <hi>Lucian</hi> a profeſs'd Atheiſt doth commend <hi>Democritus, Metrodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and <hi>Epicurus,</hi> for their conſtant adheſion to their own opinion, though never ſo much contrary to reaſon and authority: His words are theſe, ſpeaking of one <hi>Alexander</hi> a cheat, as it ſeems, and an Impoſtor, he tells you he did ſo ſtrange things,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lucian. Pſeudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantis, p. 481. Edit. Par. 1615.</note> That in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the trick ſtood in need of ſome <hi>Democritus,</hi> nay of <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curus</hi> himſelf, or <hi>Metrodorus,</hi> or ſome other that had an ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantine opinion toward that or things of the like nature, as not to believe them, and caſt about which way it might be,
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:98140:47"/>which if they could no way find, they reſolved to conclude it a lye, and impoſſible to be done, though the manner of the cheat was hid from them. Amongſt them <hi>Democritus</hi> hath endeavoured to give a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why all Divination may be natural, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, according to the opinion of the Stoick Philoſophers, nothing did ever happen in the world but by an eternal concatenation of cauſes, which have ſuch a dependance one upon another, that they render an aptitude in every thing to be foreſeen in its cauſes, which being natural, Divination may be ſo too: And <hi>Democritus</hi> farther aſſerts, that out of all things that happened by natural cauſes, there proceed certain effluxes or ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, not only in the things themſelves when exiſtent, but from their cauſes alſo; ſo that theſe cauſes being in any ſubject, may from the emanations proceeding from them give an aptitude to the ſubject to be diſpoſed accordingly; and conſequently, that the cauſe of Divination being in any man, the effluxes of it may render him a Diviner.</p>
            <p>This ſpeculation I confeſs is ſubtile, and high, if there be any ſence in it, fitter for the mouth of an Atheiſt then a Chriſtian; for admitting ſuch emanations or ſpecies may come out of material bodies, how they can proceed out of cauſes that are ſometimes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exiſtent, till they produce the effect, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times immaterial, I underſtand not. Will
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:98140:48"/>any man ſay that love, which is a paſſion, and immaterial now in any man, upon the ſight of an Object to be beloved was in him cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally either before his own exiſtence, or the exiſtence of the object; if there were ſuch effluxes in that cauſe, why not in the cauſe of that cauſe, and ſo <hi>in infinitum.</hi> Theſe ſubtile inventions to avoid manifeſt convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their own conſciences clearly ſhew there were among them undeniable teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ſuch predictions, of which no true reaſon could be given, which put them ſo to their ſhifts; becauſe they were indeed ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural: Such I take the Predictions of the Sibylls to be, but whether any or all of them were indued with the Holy Spirit of God (as I have before ſaid) remains to me queſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. This difference from them I obſerve to be in the true Prophets, that they were never during their Propheſie deprived of their wits or ſenſes; if at any time they have been ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with any conſternation or aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the appearance of an Angel, or the like, they have been by the power of God ſoon reſtored to a temper fit to underſtand, and deliver the meſſage intruſted to them: Nay they have been farther able to confirm by Miracle, that they were truly ſent by God, when it ſtood with his glory to have it ſo, and the diſtruſt of the people required it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as theſe Sibylls are never reputed to have done any other Miracle ſave that of truly foretel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling things to come. 'Tis made indeed the
<pb n="245" facs="tcp:98140:48"/>mark of a Prophet not ſent by God,
<note place="margin">Deut. 18. ult.</note> if the things foretold come not to paſs; and this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly is true; but it follows not conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibly, that where ever things foretold come to paſs, that perſon is ſent by God, except meant permiſſively; for we know the Oracles of the Heathen Gods gave often true anſwers, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſo to do indeed by God, but inſpired by the Devil. We know farther, that theſe Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylls were generally ſuppoſed in the delivery of their Oracles to be in a rapture and fury, that themſelves underſtood not what they delivered, nor were able to make perfect what was imperfectly taken by the Writer: This we have upon the authority of <hi>Virgil, Tully,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virg. Aenei. 3. Cic. de Divin. li. 2. Ovid. Met. li. 14.</note> and others: Nay, that <hi>Sibylla</hi> commonly called <hi>Erythrea,</hi> ſaith ſhe is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a rapture or fury. The conſideration of theſe things makes me prone enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they had in their predictions <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a powerful inſpiration, as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> twice calls it in his Admonitory to the Gentiles, but not true Propheteſſes of God, &amp; ſanctified by his holy Spirit, at leaſt not all, if any of them; yet do I very little doubt of their Antiquity, or ſuſpect any great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to have happened to their Books, for the genuineneſs of which we have as much to ſay, as for moſt ancient Writings left amongſt us, all or moſt of the things quoted out of them by any ancient Writer being now extant in thoſe we have, and as they now are from ancient Copies tranſmitted to us. I know
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:98140:49"/>ſome go yet higher than I do, and conceive them true propheteſſes of God, as you may ſee in the beginning of this Diſcourſe, of which opinion St <hi>Jerome</hi> ſeems to be.
<note place="margin">Jerom. lib. 1. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus Jovini. longe poſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium. Collius de Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byll. c. 35. p. 226.</note> 
               <hi>Collius</hi> in a ſtreight it ſeems what to determine, goes a middle way, and ſaith their Oracles are of two ſorts, one that concerns Chriſt, his Birth, Worſhip, or the like, theſe he thinks pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from divine inſpiration; others which concerned Kingdoms, and their Idol worſhip, he believes came from the Devil. Such a mixture of God and the Devil in the ſame perſon may ſeem hard to ſome to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, yet will not this conjecture ſeem alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether void of probability, when the caſe of <hi>Balaam</hi> is fully conſidered, who though he were a Magician and wicked perſon, yet for ought appears to the contrary, was guided in his propheſie by the Spirit of God, and yet not allways ſo in the counſel he gave to <hi>Balak,</hi> as you may read <hi>Numbers</hi> 22. and 23. Chapters.
<note place="margin">Aug. de Civit. Dei. l. 9. c. 23.</note> St <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Book of the City of God thinketh that ſhe that goes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name of <hi>Sibylla Erythrea</hi> (whom ſome think to be <hi>Sibylla Cumea</hi>) was a Citizen of the City of God, becauſe ſhe hath nothing in all her verſes tending to Idolatry, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the falſe Gods and their worſhip; men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions there the Acroſticks conteining theſe words JESUS CHRIST SONNE OF GOD THE SAVIOUR; Which the Tranſlator of that Book having turned into our tongue, I have thought fit to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe,
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:98140:49"/>for the Engliſh Readers ſake, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will not have the Book by him.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>In ſign of doomeſ-day the whole earth ſhall ſweat;</l>
               <l>Ever to reign a King in heavenly ſeat</l>
               <l>Shall come to judge all fleſh; the faithful and</l>
               <l>Unfaithful too before this God ſhall ſtand,</l>
               <l>Seeing him high with Saints in times laſt end:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Corporeal ſhall he ſit, and thence extend</l>
               <l>His doom on ſouls. The earth ſhall quitely waſte,</l>
               <l>Ruin'd oregrown with thorns; and men ſhall caſt</l>
               <l>Idols away, and treaſure; ſearching fire</l>
               <l>Shall burn the ground, and thence it ſhall inquire</l>
               <l>Through Seas and Sky, and break hells blackeſt gate;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So ſhall free light ſalute the bleſſed ſtate</l>
               <l>Of Saints; the guilty laſting flames ſhall burn;</l>
               <l>No act ſo hid but thence to light ſhall turn,</l>
               <l>Nor breaſt ſo cloſe, but God ſhall open wide;</l>
               <l>Each where ſhall cries be heard, and noiſe beſide</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of gnaſhing teeth. The Sun ſhall from the sky</l>
               <l>Fly forth, and ſtars no more move orderly.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great Heaven ſhall be diſſolv'd, the Moon depriv'd</l>
               <l>Of all her light: Places at height ativ'd,</l>
               <l>Depreſt, and Valleys raiſed to their ſeat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There ſhall be nought to mortalls high or great:</l>
               <l>Hills ſhall be levied with the plains; the Sea</l>
               <l>Endure no burthen; and the earth as they</l>
               <pb n="248" facs="tcp:98140:50"/>
               <l>Shall periſh; cleft with lightning; every Spring</l>
               <l>And River burn: The fatal trump ſhall ring,</l>
               <l>Unto the world from heaven a diſmal blaſt,</l>
               <l>Including plagues to come for ill deeds paſt.</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Chaos</hi> through the cleft Maſs ſhall be ſeen;</l>
               <l>Unto this Bar ſhall all earths Kings convene,</l>
               <l>Rivers of fire and brimſtone flowing from heav'n.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Theſe Verſes and many others in the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylline Books, carry in them a great ſhew of plainneſs and ſincerity; ſo that I could wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſubſcribe to the opinion of St <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, That ſome of them were Citizens of the City of God,</hi> were I able to fix upon any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in particular, or to ſatisfie my ſelf that any one of the Books, as they are now extant, were not a mixture of the Propheſies of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent perſons. She upon whom St <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> pitches, to wit, the <hi>Sibylla Erythrea,</hi> if there were truly any one of that Country, which to my underſtanding the words do not neceſſarily import, after ſhe had told you ſhe left <hi>Babylon</hi> in <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> ſhe hath theſe words, which I ſhould chuſe thus to render; Men call me according to the Graecian manner of another Country (to wit) of <hi>Erythrea,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, &amp;c.</l>
                     <bibl>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>b. Or. l. 3. p. 283.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </note> impudent, others the daughter of <hi>Circe</hi> and <hi>Gnoſtus.</hi> The interpunction of the words favour this conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; for if they were thus to be underſtood, Men call me born indeed at <hi>Erythre,</hi> an impudent perſon,
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:98140:50"/>according to the Graecian manner of another Country:
<note place="margin">Lact. l. 1. de falſa Relig. pa. 37. —<hi>Niſi Ery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threae quae &amp; nomen ſuum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum carmini in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruit, &amp; Ery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thream ſe nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natam iri prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locuta eſt cum eſſet orta Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loniae.</hi>
               </note> There ought to have been a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction at the firſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to ſhew us that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ought to be read in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentheſis, that the reference might truly be made; beſide the Article <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the ſecond verſe will be impertinent, and no Country at all from whence ſhe came is named. This I have inſerted here, becauſe I had in the preceding Diſcourſe ſo rendred the words, without giving any reaſon; and I find ſome conclude out of this place, that one of the Sibylls ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges her ſelf born at <hi>Erythrea;</hi> More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over that <hi>Sibylla Erythrea</hi> or <hi>Cumea,</hi> upon whom St <hi>Auguſtine</hi> pitches, was certainly that perſon whoſe books were kept in, and burnt with the Capitol, and from which the <hi>Romans</hi> fetch'd out all their ſuperſtitious fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; beſides, ſhe ſeems by <hi>Virgil</hi> to be poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the delivery of her Propheſies with that kind of madneſs and fury uſually obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the delivery of Oracles by <hi>Apollo;</hi> for which reaſons, of all others of them, I ſhould think <hi>Sibylla Cumea,</hi> if the ſame with <hi>Ery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threa,</hi> the moſt unlikely to be of the City of God, which is more likely to be true of her that came out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and foretold ſhe ſhould be counted of <hi>Enythrea.</hi> Under ſo great an uncertainty therefore and variety of opinions, I think it ſafeſt to ſuſpend my own judgment, and agree in this concluſian, That whether all or any of them were immediately guided by God, or what other ſpirit they
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:98140:51"/>ſpake by, yet were they by his power ſo over-ruled, that where in his wiſedom he thought fit, they could not lye; ſo that the truth they delivered was indeed his, though the ſpirit by which they ſpake came not from him. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this is clear, ſuch perſons there were, ſuch predictions they left, which in their due time were accompliſhed, which was all I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned to prove in this diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir, have I gone through my intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diſquiſition of the Sibylls, and in it have I hope made it appear, That the Arguments produced againſt them are not of that value to take from them the authority they have been allowed by the teſtimonies of <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Clemens Alexandrinus, Theophilus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochenſis,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tempor. Chron. An. mun.</hi> 610.</note> Lactantius,</hi> who as <hi>Temporarius</hi> ſaith, was a Prieſt of the Capitol before his converſion, and ſo permitted to read theſe Books, and many others of the Ancients, with innumerable latter Writers, amongſt whom I cannot forget two very learned Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of our own Church, <hi>Richard Montacute</hi> ſometimes Lord Biſhop of <hi>Norwich,</hi> who hath a particular Excercitation in the defence of them; and <hi>Lancelot Andrews</hi> late Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> who hath theſe words ſpeaking of the truth of Chriſtianity; For the credit of the Hiſtory it ſelf, we know that the Sibylls Oracles were in ſo great credit amongſt the Heathen, that they were general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed. Now if they be true, w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> we have of them, as there's no queſtion but many of
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:98140:51"/>them are, (divers of which we refer to Chriſt, being mentioned in their own writers, <hi>Virgil, Cicero,</hi> and others) it will follow, that nothing can make more in their eſteem for the credit and truth of the Nativity, Life, and Death of Chriſt, than their Oracles; for we may ſee almoſt every circumſtance in them.
<note place="margin">Andrews <hi>Pat of Catechiſt. Doct. Introduct. c.</hi> 12. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.</note> And by reading theſe Verſes divers of their Learned men were converted to Chriſtianity, as <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellinus, Secundanus,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>If after all this there remain yet ſome that had rather believe <hi>D. Blundel,</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers but of yeſterday, I ſhall only add, That the thing in controverſie is not of faith; and that for the truth and certainty of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, we have in the undeniable Word of God a more ſtable and un-erring Teſtimony.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
